<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Paradoxes of defence wherein is proued the true grounds of fight to be in the short auncient weapons, and that the short sword hath aduantage of the long sword or long rapier. And the weakenesse and imperfection of the rapier-fights displayed. Together with an admonition to the noble, ancient, victorious, valiant, and most braue nation of Englishmen, to beware of false teachers of defence, and how they forsake their owne naturall fights: with a briefe commendation of the noble science or exercising of armes. By George Siluer Gentleman.</title>
            <author>Silver, George, fl. 1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117412</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852626</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852626</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17956</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Paradoxes of defence wherein is proued the true grounds of fight to be in the short auncient weapons, and that the short sword hath aduantage of the long sword or long rapier. And the weakenesse and imperfection of the rapier-fights displayed. Together with an admonition to the noble, ancient, victorious, valiant, and most braue nation of Englishmen, to beware of false teachers of defence, and how they forsake their owne naturall fights: with a briefe commendation of the noble science or exercising of armes. By George Siluer Gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Silver, George, fl. 1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 72 p., plate : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Richard Field] for Edvvard Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: George Siluer his Paradoxes of defence.</note>
                  <note>The "plate" is a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fencing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17956:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17956:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PARADOXES OF DEFENCE, WHEREIN IS PROVED THE TRVE grounds of Fight to be in the ſhort auncient weapons, and that the ſhort Sword hath aduantage of the long Sword or long Rapier. And the weakeneſſe and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Rapier-fights diſplayed. Together with an Admonition to the noble, ancient, victorious, valiant, and moſt braue nation of Engliſhmen, to beware of falſe teachers of Defence, and how they forſake their owne naturall fights: with a briefe commendation of the noble ſcience or exerciſing of Armes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By George Siluer Gentleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>ANCHORA SPEI</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Edvvard Blount. 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:17956:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>HONI SOYT QVY MAL Y PENSE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17956:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, MY SINGVLAR GOOD LORD, ROBERT EARLE OF Eſſex and Ewe, Earle Marſhall of England, Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier <hi>and Louaine, Maiſter of the Queenes Maieſties horſe, &amp;</hi> of the Ordenance, Chancellor of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Knight of the moſt noble order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and one of her Highneſſe most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Priuy Counſell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ENCING (Right honorable) in this new fangled age, is like our faſhions, euerie daye a change, reſembling the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melion, who altereth himſelfe into all colours ſaue white: ſo Fencing changeth into all wards ſaue the right. That it is ſo, experience teacheth vs: why it is ſo, I doubt not but your wiſedome doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. There is nothing permanent that is not true, what can be true that is vncertaine? how can that be certaine, that ſtands vpon vncertain
<pb facs="tcp:17956:3"/> grounds? The mind of man a greedie hunter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter truth, finding the ſeeming truth but chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, not alwayes one, but alwayes diuerſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes the ſuppoſed, to find out the aſſured cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie: and ſearching euery where ſaue where it ſhould, meetes with all ſaue what it would. VVho ſeekes &amp; finds not, ſeekes in vaine; who ſeekes in vaine, muſt if he wil find ſeeke againe: and ſeeke he may againe and againe, yet all in vaine. VVho ſeekes not what he would, as he ſhould, and where he ſhould, as in all other things (Right honourable) ſo in Fencing: the mind deſirous of truth, hunts after it, and hating falſhood, flies from it, and therfore hauing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it once, it aſſayes the ſecond time: if then he thriues not, he tries another way: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath failed he aduentures on the third: &amp; if all theſe faile him, yet he neuer faileth to chaunge his weapon, his fight, his ward, if by any meanes he may compaſſe what he moſt affect: for becauſe men deſire to find out a true defence for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their fight, therefore they ſeeke it dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, nature hauing taught vs to defend our ſelues, and Art teaching how: and becauſe we miſſe it in one way we chaunge to another. But
<pb facs="tcp:17956:3"/> though we often chop and change, turne and returne, from ward to ward, from fight to fight, in this vnconſtant ſearch, yet wee neuer reſt in anie, and that becauſe we neuer find the truth:<note place="margin">Engliſh maiſters of defence, are profitable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, if they teach with ancient Engliſh weapons of true Defence, weight and conuenient length, within the compaſſe of the statures and strength of men to command, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it maketh them ſafe, bold, valiant, hardie, ſtrong and healthfull, and victoriou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the warres, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of their Prince, defence of their friendes and countrey. But the Rapter in reaſon not to be taught, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to be taught, becauſe it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnſafe in ſingle combat, and weak, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruiceable in the warres.</note> and therefore we neuer find it, becauſe we neuer ſeeke it in that weapon where it may be found. For, to ſeeke for a true defence in an vntrue weapon, is to angle on the earth for fiſh, and to hunt in the ſea for Hares: truth is ancient though it ſeeme an vpſtart: our forefathers were wiſe, though our age account them fooliſh, valiant though we repute them cowardes: they found out the true defence for their bodies in ſhort weapons by their wiſdome, they defended them ſelues and ſubdued their enemies, with thoſe weapons with their valour. And (Right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) if we will haue this true Defence, we muſt ſeeke it where it is, in ſhort Swords, ſhort Staues the halfe Pike, Partiſans, Gloues, or ſuch like weapons of perfect le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gths, not in long Swords, long Rapiers, nor frog pricking Poiniards: for if there be no certain grounds for Defence, why do they teach it? if there be, why haue they not found it? Not becauſe it is not: to ſay ſo, were to gaineſay the truth: but becauſe it is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:17956:4"/> in thoſe weapons which they teach. To proue this, I haue ſet forth theſe my Paradoxes, different I confeſſe from the maine current of our outlandiſh teachers, but agreeing I am well aſſured to the truth, and tending as I hope to the honor of our Engliſh nation. The reaſon which moued me to aduenture ſo great a taske, is the deſire I haue to bring the truth to light, which hath long time lyen hidden in the caue of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, while we like degenerate ſonnes, haue forſaken our forefathers vertues with their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and haue luſted like men ſicke of a ſtrange ague, after the ſtrange vices and deuiſes of Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, French and Spaniſh Fencers, litle remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that theſe Apiſh toyes could not free Rome from Brennius ſacke, nor Fraunce from King Henrie the fift his conqueſt. To this deſire to find out truth the daughter of time, begotten of Bellona, I was alſo moued, that by it I might remoue the great loſſe of our Engliſh gallants, which we daily ſuffer by theſe imperfect fights, wherein none vndertake the combat, be his cauſe neuer ſo good, his cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning neuer ſo much, his ſtrength and agilitie neuer ſo great, but his vertue was tied to fortune: happie man, happie
<pb facs="tcp:17956:4"/> doale, kill or be killed is the dreadfull iſſue of this diuelliſh imperfect fight. If that man were now aliue, which beat the Maiſter for the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers fault, becauſe he had no better inſtructed him, theſe Italian Fencers could not eſcape his cenſure, who teach vs Offence, not Defence, and to fight, as Diogenes ſcholers were taught to daunce, to bring their liues to an end by Art. VVas Aiax a coward becauſe he fought with a ſeuen foulded Buckler, or are we mad to go na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked into the field to trie our fortunes, not our vertues? VVas Achilles a run-away, who ware that well tempered armour, or are we deſperat, who care for nothing but to fight, and learn like the Pigmeys, to fight with bodkins, or weapons of like defence? Is it valour for a man to go na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked againſt his enemie? why then did the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians puniſh him as deſperate, whom they rewarded for his vallour with a Lawrell crowne? But that which is moſt ſhamefull,<note place="margin">To this it will be obiected, that in the warres we vſe few Rapiers or none at all, but ſhort Swords. To that I anſwere: Thoſe are inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient alſo, for that they haue no hilts, whereby they are inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which being ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken although with averie ſmal blow, most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is the loſſe of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe the force of his hand being taken from him, he is neither able to defend his life, nor greatly to offend his enemy: and againe, ſince the Rapier-fight hath bene taught, for lacke of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe they haue loſt the vſe of the blow.</note> they teach me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to butcher one another here at home in peace, wherewith they cannot hurt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abrode in warre. For, your Honour well knowes, that when the battels are ioyned, and come to the charge, there is no roome for them
<pb facs="tcp:17956:5"/> to drawe their Bird ſpits, and when they haue them, what can they doe with them? can they pierce his Corſlet with the point? can they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace his Helmet, vnbuckle his Armour, hew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder their Pikes with a <hi>Stocata,</hi> a <hi>reuerſa,</hi> a <hi>Dritta;</hi> a <hi>Stramaſon,</hi> or other ſuch like te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtuous termes? no, theſe toyes are fit for children, not for men, for ſtragling boyes of the Campe, to murder poultrie, not for men of Honour to trie the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell with their foes. Thus I haue (right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) for the trial of the truth, betweene the ſhort Sword and the long Rapier, for the ſauing of the liues of our Engliſh gallants, who are ſent to certaine death by their vncertaine fights, &amp; for abandoning of that miſchieuous and imperfect weapon, which ſerues to kill our frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in peace, but cannot much hurt our foes in warre, haue I at this time giuen forth theſe Paradoxes to the view of the world. And becauſe I knowe ſuch ſtraunge opinions had need of ſtout defence, I humbly craue your Honorable protection, as one in whom the true nobility of our victorious Aunceſtors hath taken vp his reſidence. It will ſute to the reſt of your Honours moſt noble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, to maintaine the defence of their
<pb facs="tcp:17956:5"/> weapons whoſe vertues you poſſeſſe. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agrees with your Honourable diſpoſition, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with fauour what is preſented with loue. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with your Lordſhips high authority, to weigh with reaſon, what is fit for marſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is an vſuall point of your Honor, which win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> your Lordſhip loue in your countrey, to defend the truth in whomſoeuer: and it addeth a ſupply to that vvhich your Lordſhip haue of late begun to your vnſpeakeable honor and our ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefite, to reduce the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vvith hilts ouer the hands,<note place="margin">Why ſhould we leaue the hand naked, ſince ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our limmes &amp; liues are defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, our enemies diſcomforted, wounded, and executed? I ſee no reaſon but that the hand ſhould be as well armed and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, as anie other part of the bodie.</note> to the Romaine diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, no longer then they might draw them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their armes, or ouer their ſhoulders. I call or any of theſe reſpectes, I reſt aſſured that your Lordſhip vvill vouchſafe to receiue vvith fauor and maintaine vvith honour theſe Paradoxes of mine, vvhich if they be ſhrouded vnder ſo ſafe a ſhield, I vvill not doubt but to maintaine vvith reaſon amongſt the vviſe, and proue it by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe vpon the ignorant, that there is no certaine defence in the Rapier, and that there is great aduantage in the ſhort Sword againſt the long Rapier, or all maner of Rapiers in generall, of vvhat length ſoeuer. And that the ſhort Staffe
<pb facs="tcp:17956:6"/> hath the vauntage againſt the long Staffe of twelue, foureteene, ſixteene or eighteene foote long, or of what length ſoeuer. And againſt two men vvith their Swordes and Daggers, or two Rapiers, Poiniards &amp; Gantlets, or each of them a caſe of Rapiers: vvhich vvhether I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme or not, I ſubmit for triall to your Honors martiall cenſure, being at all times readie to make it good, in vvhat maner, and againſt vvhat man ſoeuer it ſhall ſtand vvith your Lordſhips good liking to appoint. And ſo I humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this booke to your Lordſhips vviſedome to peruſe, and your Honour to the Higheſt to protect in all health and happineſſe novve and euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all dutie, <hi>George Siluer.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17956:6"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION TO THE NOBLE, ANCIENT, VICTORIOVS, VALIANT, AND MOST BRAVE NATION OF ENGLISHMEN.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eorge Siluer</hi> hauing the perfect <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> knowledge of all maner of weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and being experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in all maner of fights, thereby perceiuing the great abuſes by the <hi>Italian</hi> Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Offence done vnto them, the great errors, inconueniences, &amp; falſe reſolutions they haue brought them into haue inforced me, euen of pitie of their moſt lamentable wounds and ſlaughters, &amp; as I verily thinke it my bounden dutie, with all loue and humilitie to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them to take heed, how they ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the hands of <hi>Italian</hi> teachers of Defence, or ſtraungers whatſoeuer; and to beware how they forſake or ſuſpect their owne naturall fight, that they may by caſting off of theſe Italianated, weake, fantaſticall, and moſt diuelliſh and imperfect fights, and by exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their owne ancient weapons, be reſtored, or atchieue vnto their natural, and moſt manly and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fight againe, the dint and force whereof manie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17956:7"/> braue nations haue both felt and feared. Our plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue mightily preuailed againſt them, as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Maiſters of Defence both in Schooles and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that haue taken vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtand vpon Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trickes and iugling gambalds: whereby it grew to a common ſpeech among the countrie-men, Bring me to a Fencer, I will bring him out of his fence trickes with good downe right blowes, I will make him forget his fence trickes I will warrant him. I ſpeake not againſt Maiſters of Defence indeed, they are to be honoured, nor againſt the Science, it is noble, and in mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be preferred next to Diuinitie; for as Diuinitie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the ſoule from hell and the diuell, ſo doth this noble Science defend the bodie from wounds &amp; ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And moreouer, the exerciſing of weapons putteth away aches, griefes, and diſeaſes, it increaſeth ſtrength, and ſharpneth the wits, it giueth a perfect iudgement, it expelleth melancholy, cholericke and euill conceits, it keepeth a man in breath, perfect health, and long life. It is vnto him that hath the perfection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, a moſt friendly and comfortable companion when he is alone, hauing but only his weapon about him, it putteth him out of all feare, &amp; in the warres and places of moſt danger it maketh him bold, hardie, and valiant.</p>
            <p>And for as much as this noble and moſt mightie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Engliſhmen, of their good natures, are alwayes moſt louing, verie credulous, &amp; ready to cheriſh &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers: yet that through their good natures they neuer more by ſtrangers or falſe teachers may be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, once againe I am moſt humbly to admoniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſuch as ſhal find in themſelues a diſpoſition or deſire to learne their weapons of them, that from henceforth as
<pb facs="tcp:17956:7"/> ſtrangers ſhall take vpon them to come hither to teach this noble &amp; moſt valiant, &amp; victorious nation to fight, that firſt, before they learne of them, they cauſe a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient triall of them to be made, whether the excellencie of their skill be ſuch as they profeſſe or no, the triall to be very requiſite &amp; reaſonable, euen ſuch as I my ſelfe would be contented withall, if I ſhould take vpon me to go in their countrie to teach their nation to fight. And this is the triall:<note place="margin">A great fauor to giue them choice of their weapons, becauſe profeſſors of armes ought to be skilfull with all maner of weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> they ſhall play with ſuch weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as they profeſſe to teach withall, three bouts apeece with three of the beſt Engliſh Maiſters of Defence, &amp; three bouts apeece with three vnskilful valiant men, and three bouts apeece with three reſolute men half drunke. Then if they can defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt theſe maiſters of Defence, and hurt, and go free from the reſt, then are they to be honored, cheriſhed, and allowed for perfect good tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, what countrey men ſoeuer they be: but if of anie of theſe they take foile, then are they imperfect in their profeſſion, their fight is falſe, &amp; they are falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, deceiuers and murtherers, and to be puniſhed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, yet no worſe puniſhment vnto them I wiſh, then ſuch as in their triall they ſhall find.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>There are foure eſpeciall markes to know the Italian fight is imperfect &amp; that the Italian teachers and ſetters forth of books of Defence, neuer had the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the true fight.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he firſt marke is,<note place="margin">Yet they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs that the croſſe of the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier without hilt or gantlet is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</note> they ſeldome fight in their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> owne country vnarmed, commonly in this ſort, a paire of Gantlettes vpon their hands, and a good ſhirt of maile vpon their bodies. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d marke is, that neither the Italians, nor any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17956:8"/> of their beſt ſcholers do neuer fight, but they are moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſore hurt, or one or both of them ſlaine.</p>
               <p>The third marke is, they neuer teach their ſcholers, nor ſet downe in their bookes anie perfect lengthes of their weapons, without the which no man can by nature or Art againſt the perfect le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth fight ſafe, for being too ſhort, their times are too long, and ſpaces too wide for their defence, and being too long, they wilbe vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie croſſe that ſhall happen to be made, whether it be done by skil or chance, in great danger of death; becauſe the Rapier being too long, the croſſe cannot be vndone in due time, but may be done by going backe with the feete; but that time is alwaies too long to anſwere the time of the hand, therfore euery man ought to haue a weapon according to his owne ſtature: the tall man muſt haue his weapon longer then the man of meane ſtature, or elſe he hath wrong in his defence, &amp; the man of meane ſtature muſt haue his weapon longer then the man of ſmal ſtature, or elſe he hath wrong in his defence; &amp; the man of ſmall ſtature muſt beware that he feed not himſelf with this vaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipt, that he wil haue his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon long, to reach as farre as the tall man, for therin he ſhal haue great diſaduantage, both in making of a ſtrong croſſe, and alſo in vncroſſing againe, and in keeping his point from croſſing, and when a croſſe is made vpon him, to defend himſelf, or indanger his enemie, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme his loſt times. Againe Rapiers longer, then is conuenient to accord with the true ſtatures of men, are alwaies too long or too heauie to keepe their bodies in due time from the croſſe of the light ſhort ſword of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect length, the which being made by the skilfull out of any of the foure true times, vpon any of the foure chiefe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17956:8"/> Actions, by reaſon of the vncertaintie &amp; great ſwiftneſſe in any of theſe times, they are in great danger of a blow, or of a thruſt in the hand, arme, head, body, or face, &amp; in euerie true croſſe in the vncroſſing, in great danger of a blow vpon the head, or a full thruſt in the bodie or face: and being taken in that time &amp; place, the firſt mouer in vncroſſing ſpeedeth the Rapier man of imperfect le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, whether it be too long, too ſhort or too heauie, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth free himſelfe by the direction of his gouernours.</p>
               <p>The fourth marke is, the croſſes of their Rapiers for true defence of their hands are imperfect, for the true cariage of the guardant fight, without the which all fights are imperfect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ſixe chiefe cauſes, that many valiant men thinking themſelues by their practiſes to be skilfull in their weapons, are yet manie times in their fight ſore hurt, and manie times ſlaine by men of ſmall skill, or none at all.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt and chiefeſt cauſe is, the lacke of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> foure Gouernours, without the which it is impoſſible to fight ſafe, although a man ſhould practiſe moſt painfully and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently all the daies of his life.</p>
               <p>The ſecond cauſe is, the lacke of knowledge in the due obſeruance of the foure Actions, the which we cal bent, ſpent, lying ſpent, and drawing backe: theſe Actions e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man fighteth vpon, whether they be skilfull or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull, he that obſerueth them is ſafe, he that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, is in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall danger of euerie thruſt that ſhalbe ſtrongly made againſt him.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17956:9"/>
               <p>The third cauſe is, they are vnpractiſed in the foure true times, neither do they know the true times fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the falſe: therefore the true choiſe of their times are moſt commonly taken by chance, and ſeldome otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>The fourth cauſe is, they are vnacquainted out of what fight, or in what maner they are to anſwer the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable fight: and therefore becauſe the variable fight is the moſt eaſieſt fight of all other, moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly do an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the variable fight with the variable fight, which ought neuer to be but in the firſt diſtance, or with the ſhort Sword againſt the long, becauſe if both or one of them ſhall happen to preſe, and that in due time of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide fight be changed, the diſtance, by reaſon of nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſſe of ſpace, is broken, the place is won and loſt of both ſides, then he that thruſteth firſt, ſpeedeth: if both happen to thruſt together, they are both in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. Theſe things ſometimes by true times, by change of fights, by chance are auoided.</p>
               <p>The fift cauſe is, their weapons are moſt commonly too long to vncroſſe without going backe with the feet.</p>
               <p>The ſixt cauſe is, their weapons are moſt commonly too heauie both to defend and offend in due time, &amp; by theſe two laſt cauſes many valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue loſt their liues</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What is the cauſe that wiſemen in learning or practiſing their weapons, are deceiued with Italian Fencers.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No fight perfect that is not done in force &amp; true time.</note>THere are foure cauſes: the firſt, their ſchoolmaiſters are imperfect: the ſecond is, that whatſoeuer they teach, is both true &amp; falſe; true in their demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrations, according with their force &amp; time in ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle play, &amp; in their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17956:9"/> actions according with true force &amp; time in rough play or fight, falſe: for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, there is as much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two kind of fights, as there is betwixt the true picture of Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> himſelf, if he were liuing. The third, none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge of the Craft but the Crafts-man; the vnskilfull, be he neuer ſo wiſe, can not truly iudge of his teacher, or skill, the which he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, being vnskilful himſelfe. Laſtly, &amp; to confirme for truth all that ſhal be amiſſe, not only in this excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Defence, but in all other excellent ſecrets, moſt commonly the lye beareth as good a ſhew of truth, as truth it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the falſe reſolutions and vaine opinions of Rapier-men, and of the danger of death thereby enſuing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a great queſtion, &amp; eſpecially amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the Rapier-men, who hath the vantage of the thruſter, or of the warder. Some hold ſtrongly, that the warder hath the vantage: others ſay, it is moſt certain that the thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hath the vantage. Now when two do happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fight, being both of one mind, that the thruſter hath the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, they make all ſhift they can, who ſhall giue the firſt thruſt: as for example, two Captaines at <hi>Southampton</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they were going to take ſhipping vpon the key, fel at ſtrife, drew their Rapiers, and preſently, being deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, hardie or reſolute, as they call it, with all force and ouer great ſpeed, ran with their rapiers one at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; were both ſlaine. Now when two of the contrary opinion ſhall meet and fight, you ſhall ſee verie peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble warres betweene them: for they verily thinke that he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17956:10"/> that firſt thruſteth is in great danger of his life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with all ſpeede do put themſelues in ward, or Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata, the ſureſt gard of all other, as <hi>Vincentio</hi> ſaith, and therevpon they ſtand ſure, ſaying the one to the other, thruſt and thou dare; and ſaith the other, thruſt and thou dare, or ſtrike or thruſt and thou dare, ſaith the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then ſaith the other, ſtrike or thruſt and thou dare for thy life. Theſe two cunning gentlemen ſtanding long time together, vpon this worthie ward, they both depart in peace, according to the old prouerbe: It is good ſleeping in a whole skinne. A gaine if two ſhall fight, the one of opinion, that he that thruſteth hath the vantage, and the other of opinion, that the warder hath the vantage, then moſt commonly the thruſter being valiant, with all ſpeed thruſteth home, and by reaſon of the time and ſwift motion of his hand, they are moſt commonly with the points of their rapiers, or daggers, or both, one or both of them hurt or ſlaine; becauſe their ſpaces of defence in that kind of fight, are too wide in due time to defend, and the place being wonne, the eye of the Patient by the ſwift motion of the Agents hand, is deceiued. Another reſolution they ſtand ſure vpon for their liues, to kill their enemies, in the which they are moſt commonly ſlaine themſelues: that is this: When they find the point of their enemies rapier out of the right line, they ſay, they may boldly make home a thruſt with a <hi>Paſsata,</hi> the which they obſerue, and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: but the other hauing a ſhorter time with his hand, as nature manie times teacheth him, ſodainly tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his wriſt, whereby he meeteth the other in his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage iuſt with the point of his rapier in the face or body. And this falſe reſolution hath coſt manie a life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17956:10"/>
               <head>That the cauſe that manie are ſo often ſlaine, and manie ſore hurt in fight with long Rapiers, is not by reaſon of their dangerous thruſts, nor cunningneſſe of that Italienated fight, but in the length and vnweildineſſe thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is moſt certaine, that men may with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſhort ſwords both ſtrike, thruſt, falſe and double, by reaſon of their diſtance and nimbleneſſe thereof, more dangerouſly then they can with long Rapiers: and yet when two fight with ſhort ſwordes, hauing true fight, there is no hurt done: neither is it poſſible in anie reaſon, that anie hurt ſhould be done betwixt them of either ſide, and this is well knowne to all ſuch as haue the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of true fight. By this it plainely appeareth, that the cauſe of the great ſlaughter, and ſundrie hurts done by long Rapiers, conſiſteth not in long Reach, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thruſtes, nor cunningneſſe of the Italian fight, but in the inconuenient length, and vnweildineſſe of their long Rapiers: whereby it commonly falleth out, that in all their Actions appertaining to their defence, they are vnable, in due time to performe, and continually in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of euerie croſſe, that ſhall happen to be made with their rapier blades, which being done, within the halfe rapier; (vnleſſe both be of one mind with all ſpeed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, which ſeldome or neuer hapneth betweene men of valiant diſpoſition,) it is impoſſible to vncroſſe, or get out, or to auoid the ſtabbes of the Daggers. And this hath falne out manie times amongſt valiant men at thoſe weapons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17956:11"/>
               <head>Of running and ſtanding faſt in Rapier fight, the runner hath the vantage.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F two valiant men do fight being both cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in running, &amp; that they both vſe the ſame at one inſtant, their courſe is doubled, the place is wonne of both ſides, and one or both of them will commonly be ſlaine or ſore hurt: and if one of them ſhall runne, and the other ſtand faſt vpon the <hi>Imbrocata</hi> or <hi>Stocata,</hi> or howſoeuer, the place wilbe at one inſtant wonne of one ſide, and gained of the other, and one or both of them wilbe hurt or ſlaine: if both ſhall preſe hard vpon the guard, he that firſt thruſteth home in true place, hurteth the other: &amp; if both thruſt together, they are both hurt: yet ſome vantage the runner hath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is an vncertaine marke, and in his motion: the other is a certaine marke, and in a dead motion: and by reaſon thereof manie times the vnskilfull man taketh vantage he knoweth not how, againſt him that lyeth watching vpon his ward or <hi>Stocata</hi> guard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ſtriking and thruſting both together.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> It is ſtrongly holden of manie, that if in fight they find their enemy to haue more skill then themſelues, they preſently will continually ſtrike, &amp; thruſt iuſt with him, whereby they will make their fight as good as his, and thereby haue as good aduantage as the other with all his skill: but if their ſwordes be longer then the other, then their aduantage is great; for it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17956:11"/> certaine (ſay they) that an inch will kill a man: but if their ſwordes be much longer then the other, then their aduantage is ſo great, that they wilbe ſure by thruſting and ſtriking iuſt with the other, that they will alwaies hurt him that hath the ſhort ſword, and go cleare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, becauſe they will reach him, when he ſhall not reach them. Theſe men ſpeake like ſuch as talke of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin Hoode, that neuer ſhot in his bow; for to ſtrike or thruſt iuſt together with a man of skill, lyeth not in the will of the ignorant, becauſe the skilfull man alwaies fighteth vpon the true times, by the which the vnskilfull is ſtill diſappointed of both place and time, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore driuen of neceſſitie ſtill to watch the other, when &amp; what he will doe; that is, whether he will ſtrike, thruſt, or falſe: if the vnskilfull ſtrike or thruſt in the time of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, therein he neither ſtriketh nor thruſteth iuſt with the other: he may ſaie, he hath ſtroke or thruſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, but not iuſt with him, nor to anie good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for in the time of falſing, if he ſtrike or thruſt, he ſtriketh or thruſteth too ſhort: for in that time he hath neither time nor place to ſtrike home, and as it is ſaid, the vnskilfull man, that will take vpon him to ſtrike or thruſt iuſt with the skilfull, muſt firſt behold what the man of skil will doe, and when he will doe it, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of neceſſitie is driuen to ſuffer the skilfull man to be the firſt mouer, and entred into his Action, whether it be blow or thruſt, the truth therof in reaſon cannot be denied. Now iudge whether it be poſſible for an vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man to ſtrike or thruſt iuſt together with a man of skill; but the skilfull man can moſt certainly ſtrike and thruſt iuſt together with the vnskilfull, becauſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull fighteth vpon falſe times, which being too long
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17956:12"/> to anſwere the true times, the skilfull fighting vpon the true times, although the vnskilfull be the firſt mouer, &amp; entred into his Action, whether it be blow or thruſt; yet the ſhortneſſe of the true times maketh at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the skilfull a iuſt meeting together: in perfect fight two neuer ſtrike or thruſt together, becauſe they neuer ſuffer place nor time to performe it.</p>
               <p>Two vnskilfull men manie times by chance ſtrike and thruſte together, chance vnto them, becauſe they know not what they doe, or how it commeth to paſſe: but the reaſons or cauſes be theſe. Sometimes two falſe times meet &amp; make a iuſt time together, &amp; ſometimes a true time and a falſe time meeteth and maketh a iuſt time together, and ſometimes two true times meet and make a iuſt time together. And all this hapneth becauſe the true time and place is vnknowne vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>George Siluer his reſolution vpon that hidden or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full queſtion, who hath the aduantage of the Offender or Defender.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he aduantage is ſtrongly holden of many to be in the offender, yea in ſomuch, that if two minding to offend in their fight, it is thought to be in him that firſt ſtriketh or thruſteth. Others ſtrongly hold opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the warder abſolutely hath ſtill the adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, but theſe opinions as they are contrary the one to the other: ſo are they contrarie to true fight, as may well be ſeene by theſe ſhort examples. If the aduantage be in the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then it is not good anie time to ſtrike or thruſt: if the aduantage be in the ſtriker or thruſter, then were it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17956:12"/> a friuolous thing to learne to ward, or at anie time to ſeeke to ward, ſince in warding lieth diſaduantage. Now may it plainly by theſe examples appeare, that if there be anie perfection in fight, that both ſides are deceiued in their opinions, becauſe if the ſtriker or thruſter haue the aduantage, then is the warder ſtill in danger of wounds or death. And againe, if the warder hath the aduantage, then is the ſtriker or thruſter in as great daunger to defend himſelfe againſt the warder, becauſe the warder from his wards, taketh aduantage of the ſtriker or thruſter vpon euerie blow or thruſt, that ſhall be made againſt him. Then thus I conclude, that if there be perfection in the Science of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, they are all in their opinons deceiued; and that the truth may appeare for the ſatisfaction of all men, this is my reſolution: there is no aduantage abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor diſaduantage in ſtriker, thruſter, or warder: and there is a great aduantage in the ſtriker thruſter &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: but in this maner, in the perfection of fight the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage conſiſteth in fight betweene partie and partie: that is, whoſoeuer winneth or gaineth the place in true pace, ſpace and time, hath the aduantage, whether he be ſtriker, thruſter or warder. And that is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Spanish fight vvith the Rapier.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Spaniard</hi> is now thought to be a better <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> man with his Rapier then is the Italian, Frenchman, high Almaine, or anie other countrie man whatſoeuer, becauſe they in their Rapier-fight ſtand vpon ſo manie intricate trickes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17956:13"/> that in all the courſe of a mans life it ſhall be hard to learne them, and if they miſſe in doing the leaſt of them in their fight, they are in danger of death. But the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> in his fight, both ſafely to defend himſelfe, and to endanger his enemie, hath but one onely lying, and two wards to learne, wherein a man with ſmall practiſe in a verie ſhort time may become perfect.</p>
               <p>This is the maner of Spaniſh fight, they ſtand as braue as they can with their bodies ſtraight vpright, narrow ſpaced, with their feet continually mouing, as if they were in a dance, holding forth their armes and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers verie ſtraight againſt the face or bodies of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: &amp; this is the only lying to accompliſh that kind of fight. And this note, that as long as any man ſhall lie in that maner with his arme, and point of his Rapier ſtraight, it ſhall be impoſſible for his aduerſarie to hurt him, becauſe in that ſtraight holding forth of his arme, which way ſoeuer a blow ſhall be made againſt him, by reaſon that his Rapier hilt lyeth ſo farre before him, he hath but a verie litle way to moue, to make his ward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in this maner. If a blow be made at the right ſide of the head, a verie litle mouing of the hand with the knuckles vpward defendeth that ſide of the head or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and the point being ſtill out ſtraight, greatly endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gereth the ſtriker: and ſo likewiſe, if a blow be made at the left ſide of the head, a verie ſmall turning of the wriſt with the knuckles downward, defendeth that ſide of the head and bodie, and the point of the Rapier much indangereth the hand, arme, face or bodie of the ſtriker: and if anie thruſt be made, the wards, by reaſon of the indirections in mouing the feet in maner of dauncing, as aforeſaid, maketh a perfect ward, and ſtill withall the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17956:13"/> point greatly endangereth the other. And thus is the Spaniſh fight perfect: ſo long as you can keepe that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſoone learned, and therefore to be accounted the beſt fight with the Rapier of all other. But note how this Spaniſh fight is perfect, and you ſhall ſee no longer then you can keepe your point ſtraight againſt your aduerſarie: as for example, I haue heard the like ieſt.</p>
               <p>There was a cunning Doctor at his firſt going to ſea, being doubtfull that he ſhould be ſea-ſicke, an old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man perceiuing the ſame, ſaid vnto him: Sir, I pray, be of good comfort, I will teach you a tricke to auoid that doubt; here is a fine pibble ſtone, if you pleaſe to accept it, take it with you, and when you be on ſhip-bord, put it in your mouth, and as long as you ſhall keepe the ſame in your mouth, vpon my credit you ſhall neuer vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: the Doctor beleeued her, and tooke it thankfully at her hands, and when he was at ſea, he began to be ſicke, whereupon he preſently put the ſtone in his mouth, &amp; there kept it ſo long as he poſſibly could, but through his extreme ſickneſſe the ſtone with vomit was caſt out of his mouth: then preſently he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred how the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had mocked him, and yet her words were true.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo a <hi>Spaniard</hi> hauing his Rapier point put by, may receiue a blow on the head, or a cut ouer the face, hand, or arme, or a thruſt in the body or face, and yet his Spaniſh fight perfect, ſo long as he can keepe ſtraight the point of his Rapier againſt the face or body of his aduerſarie: which is as eaſie in that maner of fight to be done, as it was for the Doctor in the extremity of his vomite to keepe the ſtone in his mouth.</p>
               <p>Yet one other pretie ieſt more, ſcarce worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17956:14"/> in commendation of outlandiſh fight. There was an <hi>Italian</hi> teacher of Defence in my time, who was ſo excellent in his fight, that he would haue hit anie En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh man with a thruſt, iuſt vpon any button in his dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet, and this was much ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>Alſo there was another cunning man in catching of wild geeſe, he would haue made no more ado, when he had heard them crie, as the maner of wildgeeſe is, flying one after another in rowes, but preſently looking vp, would tell them, if there had bene a doſen, ſixteene, twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or more, he would haue taken euerie one. And this tale was manie times told by men of good credit, and much maruelled at by the hearers: &amp; the man that wold haue taken the wildgeeſe, was of good credite himſelfe: marie they ſaid, indeed he did neuer take anie, but at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie time when he had looked vp, and ſeene them flie in that maner, he would with all his heart haue taken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but he could no more tell how to do it, then could the cunning <hi>Italian</hi> Fencer tell how to hit an Engliſhman, with a thruſt iuſt vpon any one of his buttons, when he liſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Illuſions for the maintenance of imperfect weapons &amp; falſe fights, to feare or diſcourage the vnskilfull in their weapons, from taking a true courſe or vſe, for attaining to the perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of true fight.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, for the Rapier (ſaith the <hi>Italian,</hi> or falſe teacher) I hold it to be a perfect good wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe the croſſe hindreth not to hold the handle in the hand, to thruſt both far &amp; ſtraight, &amp; to vſe all maner of aduantages in the wards,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17956:14"/> or ſodainly to caſt the ſame at the aduerſarie, but with the Sword you are driuen with all the ſtrength of the hand to hold faſt the handle. And in the warres I would wiſh no friend of mine to weare Swords with hilts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when they are ſodainly ſet vpon, for haſte they ſet their hands vpon their hilts in ſteed of their handles: in which time it hapneth manie times before they can draw their ſwords, they are ſlaine by their enemies.<note place="margin">Theſe counterfeit ſhews are enough to cary the wiſeſt that know not the true fight fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the falſe, out of the right way.</note> And for Sword and Buckler fight, it is imperfect, becauſe the buckler blindeth the fight, neither would I haue anie man lie aloft with his hand aboue his head, to ſtrike ſound blowes: Strong blowes are naught, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet aboue the head,<note place="margin">And if their wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons were ſhort, as in times paſt they were, yet they could not thrust ſafe at bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or face, becauſe in gardant fight they fall ouer, or vnder the perfect croſſe of the ſword &amp; to ſtrike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the waſte, or at the legges, is great diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, becauſe the courſe of the blow to the legs is too far, &amp; therby the head, face, &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is diſcouered: and that was the cauſe in old time, that they did not thruſt nor ſtrike at the legs, &amp; not for lacke of skill, as in theſe daies we imagine. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if a man in thoſe daies ſhold haue fought with a long ſword, they would preſently haue put him into Cobbes Trauers.</note> becauſe therein all the face and bodie is diſcouered. Yet I confeſſe, in old times, when blowes were only vſed with ſhort Swords &amp; bucklers, &amp; back Sword, theſe kind of fights were good &amp; moſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but now in theſe daies fight is altered. Rapiers are lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſwords were wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blowes were vſed, men were ſo ſimple in their fight, that they thought him to be a coward, that wold make a thruſt or ſtrike a blow beneath the girdle. Againe, if their weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were ſhort, as in times paſt they were, yet fight is better looked into in theſe dayes, than then it was. Who is it in theſe daies ſeeth not that the blow co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſeth round like a wheele, whereby it hath a longer way to go, but the thruſt paſſeth in a ſtraight line, and therefore commeth a nearer way, and done in a ſhorter time the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the blow, and is more deadly then is the blow? Therefore there is no wiſe man that will ſtrike; vnleſſe he be wearie of his life. It is certaine, that the point for aduantage euerie way in fight is to be vſed, the blow is vtterly naught, and not to be vſed. He that fighteth vpon the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17956:15"/> blow eſpecially with a ſhort ſword, wilbe ſore hurt or ſlaine. The deuill can ſay no more for the maintenance of errors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That a blow commeth continually as neare a way as a thruſt, and moſt commonly nearer, ſtronger, more ſwifter, and is ſooner done.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He blow, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it compaſſeth round like a wheele,<note place="margin">A confutation of their errours.</note> whereby it hath a longer way to come, as the Italian Fenſer ſaith, &amp; that the thruſt paſſing in a ſtraight line, commeth a nearer way, and therefore is ſooner done then a blow, is not true: theſe be the proofes.</p>
               <p>Let two lie in their perfect ſtrengths and readineſſe, wherein the blades of their Rapiers by the motion of the body, may not be croſſed of either ſide, the one to ſtrike, and the other to thruſt. Then meaſure the diſtance or courſe wherein the hand and hilt paſſeth to finiſh the blow of the one, and the thruſt of the other, and you ſhall find them both by meaſure, in diſtance all one. And let anie man of iudgement being ſeene in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of weapons, not being more addicted vnto nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of fight, then vnto truth it ſelfe, put in meaſure, and practiſe theſe three fights, variable, open, and guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and he ſhall ſee, that whenſoeuer anie man lyeth at the thruſt vpon the variable fight, (where of neceſſitie moſt commonly he lyeth, or otherwiſe not poſſiblie to keepe his Rapier from croſſing at the blow &amp; thruſt, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the open or gardant fight,) that the blowes &amp; thruſtes from theſe two fightes, come a nearer way, and a more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17956:15"/> ſtronger and ſwifter courſe then doth the thruſt, out of the variable fight. And thus for a generall rule, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Thruſter lyeth, or out of what fight ſoeuer he fighteth, with his Rapier, or Rapier and Dagger, the blow in his courſe commeth as neare, and nearer, and more ſwift and ſtronger then doth the thruſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Perfect fight ſtandeth vpon both blow and thruſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the thruſt is not onely to be vſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat there is no fight perfect without both <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> blow and thruſt: neither is there anie cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rule to be ſet downe for the vſe of the point onely, theſe be the reaſons:<note place="margin">This in truth cannot be denied.</note> In fight there are manie motions, with the hand, bodie, and feet, and in euerie motion the place of the hand is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; becauſe by the motions of the hand, the altering of the places of the hand, the changes of lyings, wards, and breaking of thruſtes, the hand will ſometimes be in place to ſtrike, ſome times to thruſt, ſometimes after a blow to thruſt, and ſometimes after a thruſt to ſtrike, &amp; ſometimes in place where you may ſtrike, and cannot thruſt without loſſe of time, and ſometimes in place where you may thruſt, and cannot ſtrike without loſſe of time, and ſometimes in place where you can neither ſtrike nor thruſt, vnleſſe you fight vpon both blow and thruſt, nor able to defend your ſelfe by ward or going backe, becauſe your ſpace wilbe too wide, and your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance loſt. And ſometimes when you haue made a thruſt, a ward or breaking is taken in ſuch ſort with the Dagger or blade of the Sword, that you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither thruſt againe, nor defend yourſelfe vnleſſe you do ſtrike, which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17956:16"/> you may foundly doe, and go free, and ſometimes when you ſtrike, a ward wilbe taken in ſuch ſort, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtrike againe, nor defend your ſelfe, vnleſſe you thruſt, which you may ſafely doe and goe free. So to conclude, there is no perfection in the true fight, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out both blow and thruſt, nor certaine rule to be ſet downe for the point onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the blow is more dangerous and deadly in fight, then a thruſt, for proofe thereof to be made according with Art, an Englishman holdeth argument againſt an Italian.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Italian.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich is more dangerous or deadly in fight of a blow or a thruſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Englishman.</speaker>
                  <p>This queſtion is not propounded ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to art, becauſe there is no fight perfect without both blow and thruſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Italian.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it be ſo, yet opinions are otherwiſe holden, that the thruſt is onely to be vſed, becauſe it commeth a nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer way, and is more dangerous and deadly, for theſe reaſons: firſt the blow compaſſeth round like a wheele, but the thruſt paſſeth in a ſtraight line, therfore the blow by reaſon of the compaſſe, hath a longer way to go then the thruſt, &amp; is therefore longer in doing, but the thruſt paſſeth in a ſtraight line, therfore hath ſhorter way to go the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath the blow, &amp; is therfore done in a ſhorter time, &amp; is therfore much better then the blow, &amp; more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deadly, becauſe if a thruſt do hit the face or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, it indangereth life, and moſt commonly death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth: but if the blow hit the bodie, it is not ſo da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17956:16"/>
                  <speaker>Englishman.</speaker>
                  <p>Let your opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be what they wil, but that the thruſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a nearer way; &amp; is ſooner done then the blow, is not true: &amp; for proofe thereof reade the twelfth Paradox. And now will I ſet downe probable reaſons,<note place="margin">The blow more dangerous then the thruſt.</note> that the blow is better then the thruſt, and more dangerous and deadly. Firſt, the blow commeth as neare a way, &amp; moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly nearer then doth the thruſt, &amp; is therfore done in a ſhorter time then is the thruſt: therfore in reſpect of time, wherupon ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the perfection of fight, the blow is much better then the thruſt. Againe, the force of the thruſt paſſeth ſtraight, therefore any croſſe being indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly made, the force of a child may put it by: but the force of a blow paſſeth indirectly, therefore muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly warded in the counterchecke of his force: which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be done but by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient ſtrength of a man, &amp; with true croſſe in true time, or elſe wil not ſafely defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him: and is therfore much better, &amp; more da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thruſt, and againe, the thruſt being made through the hand, arme, or leg, or in many places of the body and face, are not deadly, neither are they maimes, or loſſe of limmes or life, neither is he much hindred for the time in his fight, as long as the bloud is hot: for example.</p>
                  <p>I haue knowne a Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurt in Rapier fight, in nine or ten places through the bodie, armes, and legges, and yet hath continued in his fight, &amp; afterward hath ſlaine the other,<note place="margin">The blow cutteth off the hand, the arme, the leg, and ſometimes the head.</note> and come home and hath bene cured of all his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds without maime, &amp; is yet liuing. But the blow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly made, taketh ſomtimes cleane away the hand from the arme, hath manie times bene ſeene. Againe, a full blow vpon the head or face with a ſhort ſharpe Sword, is moſt commonly death. A full blow vpon the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17956:17"/> necke, ſhoulder, arme, or legge, indangereth life, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth off the veines, muſcles, and ſinewes, periſheth the bones: theſe wounds made by the blow, in reſpect of perfect healing, are the loſſe of limmes, or maimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable for euer.</p>
                  <p>And yet more for the blow: a ful blow vpon the head, face, arme, leg, or legs, is death, or the partie ſo woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the mercie of him that ſhall ſo wound him. For what man ſhall be able long in fight to ſtand vp, either to reuenge, or defend himſelfe, hauing the veines, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcles, and ſinewes of his hand, arme, or leg cleane cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder? or being diſmembred by ſuch wound vpon the face or head, but ſhall be enforced therby, and through the loſſe of bloud,<note place="margin">He that giueth the firſt wound with a ſtrong blow, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the life of the other.</note> the other a litle dallying with him, to yeeld himſelf, or leaue his life in his mercie?</p>
                  <p>And for plainer deciding this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie betweene the blow and the thruſt, conſider this ſhort note. The blow commeth manie wayes, the thruſt doth not ſo. The blow commeth a nearer way then a thruſt moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and is therefore ſooner done. The blow requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſtrength of a man to be warded; but the thruſt may be put by, by the force of a child. A blow vpon the hand, arme, or legge is a maime incurable; but a thruſt in the hand, arme, or legge is to be recouered. The blow hath manie parts to wound, and in euerie of them commaundeth the life; but the thruſt hath but a few, as the bodie or face, and not in euerie part of them neither.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17956:17"/>
               <head>Of the difference betwixt the true fight &amp; the falſe: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſiſteth (the Principles being had with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the foure Gouernors) the whole perfection of fight with all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of weapons.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He true fights be theſe: whatſoeuer is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> done with the hand before the foot or feet is true fight. The falſe fights be theſe: whatſoeuer is done with the foot or feet before the hand, is falſe, becauſe the hand is ſwifter then the foot, the foot or feet being a ſlower mouer then the hand: the hand in that maner of fight is tied to the time of the foot or feet, and being tied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, hath loſt his freedome, and is made thereby as ſlow in his motions as the foot or feet: and therfore that fight is falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of euill orders or customes in our English Fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce-ſchooles, &amp; of the old or ancient teaching of weapons, &amp; things very neceſſarie to be continued for the auoiding of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and reuining and continuance of our ancient vveapons, and moſt victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fight againe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is in my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our Fence-ſchooles <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> an euill order or cuſtome in theſe dayes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the which, if it might ſtand with the good liking of our Maiſters of Defence, I thinke it neceſſarie to be left: for as long as it is vſed, it ſhall be hard to make a good Scholler.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17956:18"/> That is this, at the ſingle Sword, Sword and Dagger, &amp; Sword and Buckler, they forbid the thruſt, &amp; at the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Rapier, and Rapier &amp; Dagger, they forbid the blow. Either they are both together beſt, or the thruſt altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſt, or the blow altogether beſt. If the thruſt be beſt, why do we not vſe it at the ſingle Sword, Sword &amp; Dagger, &amp; Sword and Buckler. If the blow be beſt, why do we not vſe it at the ſingle Rapier, Rapier &amp; Poinyard? But knowing by the Art of Armes, that no fight is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect without both blow and thruſt, why do we not vſe and teach both blow and thruſt? But howſoeuer this we dayly ſee, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two meet in fight, whether they haue skill or none, vnleſſe ſuch as haue tied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to that boyiſh, <hi>Italian,</hi> weake, imperfect fight, they both ſtrike and thruſt, and how ſhall he then do, that being much taught in ſchoole, neuer learned to ſtrike, nor how to defend a ſtrong blow? &amp; how ſhall he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do, that being brought vp in Fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce-ſchoole, that neuer learned to thruſt with the ſingle Sword, Sword and Dagger, and Sword and Buckler, nor how at theſe weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to breake a thruſt? Surely, I thinke a downe right fellow, that neuer came in ſchoole, vſing ſuch skill as nature yeeldeth out of his courage, ſtrength, and agilitie, with good downe right blowes and thruſts among, as ſhall beſt frame in his hands, ſhold put one of theſe imperfect ſchollers great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his ſhifts. Beſides, there are now in theſe dayes no gripes, cloſes, wreſtlings, ſtriking with the hilts, dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or bucklers, vſed in Fence-ſchooles. Our plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men by nature wil do all theſe things with great ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; agility: but the Schooleman is altogether vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with theſe things. He being faſt tyed to ſuch ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play as he hath learned, hath loſt thereby the benefite
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17956:18"/> of nature, and the plowman is now by nature without art a farre better man then he. Therefore in my opinion, as long as we barre anie maner of play in ſchoole, we ſhall hardly make a good ſcholler: there is no maner of teaching comparable to the old ancient teaching, that is, firſt their quarters, then their wardes, blowes, thruſts, and breaking of thruſtes, then their Cloſes and Gripes, ſtriking with the hilts, Daggers, Bucklers, Wraſtlings, ſtriking with the foote or knee in the Coddes, and all theſe are ſafely defended in learning perfectly of the Gripes. And this is the ancient teaching,<note place="margin">In the warres there is no obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Stocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, Imbro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uas, times, nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</note> the perfecteſt &amp; moſt beſt teaching; and without this teaching, there ſhall neuer ſcholler be made able, doe his vttermoſt, nor fight ſafe. Againe their ſwordes in ſchooles are too long by almoſt halfe a foote to vncroſſe, without going backe with the feete, within diſtance or perfectly to ſtrike or thruſt within the halfe or quarter ſword. And in ſeruing of the Prince, when men do meet together in publique fight, are vtterly naught and vnſeruiceable. The beſt lengthes for perfect teaching of the true fight to be vſed and continued in Fence ſchooles,<note place="margin">Long weapons imperfect.</note> to accord with the true ſtatures of all men, are theſe. The blade to be a yard and an inch for meane ſtatures, and for men of tall ſtatures, a yard and three or foure inches, and no more. And I would haue the Rapier continued in ſchooles, alwaies readie for ſuch as ſhall thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues cunning, or ſhall haue delight to play with that imperfect weapon. Prouided alwaies, that the Schoole-maiſter or Vſher play with him with his ſhort Sword, plying him with all maner of fight according to the true art: this being continued the truth ſhall flouriſh, the lye ſhalbe beaten downe, and all nations not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17956:19"/> the true ſcience, ſhall come with all gladneſſe to the valiant and moſt braue Engliſh maiſters of Defence to learne the true fight for their defence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The grounds or Principles of true fight with all maner of weapons.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt Iudgement, Lyings, Diſtance, Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Paſe, Space, Place, Time, Indirecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Motion, Action, generall and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Motion, Progreſſion, Regreſſion, Trauerſing, and Treading of groundes, Blowes, Thruſtes, Faulſes, Doubles, Slipes, Wardes, breakings of Thruſts, Cloſings, Gripes, &amp; Wraſtlings, Guardant fight, Open fight, Variable fight, and Cloſe fight, and foure Gouernours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The wardes of all maner of weapons.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L ſingle weapons haue foure wardes, and all double weapons haue eight wardes. The ſingle ſword hath two with the point vp, and two with the point downe. The Staffe and all maner of weapons to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with both handes haue the like.</p>
               <p>The Sword and Buckler, and Sword and Dagger are double weapons, and haue eight wardes, two with the point vp, and two with the point downe, and two for the legges with the point downe, the point to be caried for both ſides of the legges, with the knuckles downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and two wardes with the Dagger or Buckler for the head. The Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt bill is a double weapon by reaſon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17956:19"/> of the head, and therefore hath eight wardes, foure with the Staffe, foure with the head, foure of them to be vſed as with the ſtaffe, and the other foure with the head, the one vp, the other downe, and the other ſidewaies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The names and numbers of times appertaining vnto fight both true and falſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are eight times, whereof foure are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> true, and foure are falſe: the true times be theſe.</p>
               <p>The time of the hand.</p>
               <p>The time of the hand and bodie.</p>
               <p>The time of the hand, bodie and foote.</p>
               <p>The time of the hand, bodie and feete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The falſe times be theſe.</head>
               <p>The time of the foote.</p>
               <p>The time of the foote and bodie.</p>
               <p>The time of the foote, bodie and hand.</p>
               <p>The time of the feete, bodie and hand.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I thought good to ſeparate and make knowne the true times from the falſe, with the true wardes thereto belonging, that thereby the rather in practiſing of weapons, a true courſe may be taken for the auoiding of errours and euill cuſtomes, and ſpeedie attaining of good habit or perfect being in the true vſe and knowledge of all maner of weapons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the length of weapons, and how euerie man may fit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the perfect length of his weapon, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne ſtature, with briefe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wherefore they ought to be ſo.</head>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17956:20"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O know the perfect length of your Sword, you ſhall ſtand with your ſword and dagger drawn, as you ſee this picture, keeping out ſtraight your dagger arme, drawing backe your ſword as far as conueniently you can, not opening the elbow ioynt of your ſword arme: and looke what you can draw within your dagger, that is the iuſt length of your ſword, to be made according to your owne ſtature.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man with swords</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:17956:20"/>
               <p>AS I haue here made a figuratiue demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, to know the perfect length of the Sword, as afore is ſayd; ſo haue I in the page fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, for the plainer vnderſtanding of the Reader, ſet foorth a forme of ſtanding, to know the lengths of the ſhort Staffe, halfe Pike, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Bill, Partiſan and Gleue, or ſuch like weapons of aduantage, as ſhall alſo beſt fit the ſtatures of all men.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:17956:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man with pike</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17956:21"/>
               <p>The perfect length of your two hand ſword is, the blade to be the length of the blade of your ſingle ſword.</p>
               <p>To know the perfect length of your ſhort ſtaffe, or half Pike, Forreſt bil, Partiſan, or Gleue, or ſuch like wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of vantage and perfect lengths, you ſhall ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, holding the ſtaffe vpright cloſe by your body, with your left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, reaching with your right hand your ſtaffe as high as you can, and then allow to that length a ſpace to ſet both your hands, when you come to ſight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may conueniently ſtrike, thruſt, and ward, &amp; that is the iuſt length to be made according to your ſtature. And this note, that theſe lengths will commonly fall out to be eight or nine foot long, and will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, although not iuſt, the ſtatures of all men, without any hindrance at all vnto them in their fight, becauſe in any weapon wherin the hands may be remoued, and at libertie, to make the weapon lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger or ſhorter in fight at his pleaſure, a foot of the ſtaffe behind the backmoſt hand doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o harme. And wherfore theſe weapons ought to be of the lengths aforeſaid, and no ſhorter, theſe are the reaſons: If they ſhould be ſhorter, then the long ſtaffe, Morris Pike, and ſuch like weapons ouer and aboue the perfect length, ſhould haue great vantage againſt them becauſe he may come boldly and ſafe without anie gard or ward, to the place where he may thruſt home, and at euery thruſt put him in danger of his life: but if theſe weapons be of their perfect lengths, then can the long ſtaffe, the Morris Pike, or anie other longer weapon ly no where in true ſpace, but ſhall be ſtill within compaſſe of the croſſe, to croſſe and vncroſſe, wherby he may ſafely paſſe home to the place, where he may ſtrike or thruſt him that hath the long weapon, in the head, face, or body at his pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17956:22"/>
               <head>Of the lengths of the Battel axe, Halbard, or blacke Bill, or ſuch like vveapons of weight, appertaining vnto gard or battell.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N anie of theſe weapons there needeth no iuſt length, but commonly they are, or ought to be fiue or ſixe foot long, &amp; may not well be vſed much longer, becauſe of their weights: and being weapons for the warres or battell, when men are ioyned cloſe together, may thruſt, &amp; ſtrike ſound blowes, with great force both ſtrong and quicke: and finally for the iuſt lengths of all other ſhorter or longer weapons to be gouerned with both hands, there is none: neither is there anie certaine lengthes in anie maner of weapons to be vſed with one hand, ouer or vnder the iuſt length of the ſingle ſword.</p>
               <trailer>Thus endeth the length of weapons.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the vantages of weapons in their kinds, places, &amp; times, both in priuate and publike fight.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt I will begin with the worſt weapon, an imperfect and inſufficient weapon, and not worth the ſpeaking of; but now being highly eſteemed, therefore not to be left vnremembred; that is, the ſingle Rapier, and Rapier and Poiniard.</p>
               <p>The ſingle Sword hath the vantage againſt the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Rapier.</p>
               <p>The Sword and Dagger hath the vantage againſt the Rapier and Poiniard.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17956:22"/>
               <p>The Sword &amp; Target hath adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage againſt the Sword and Dagger, or Rapier and Poiniard.</p>
               <p>The Sword and Buckler hath aduantage againſt the Sword and Target, the Sword and Dagger, or Rapier and Poiniard.</p>
               <p>The two hand Sword, hath the vantage againſt the Sword and Target, the Sword and Buckler, the Sword and Dagger, or Rapier and Poiniard.</p>
               <p>The Battel-axe, the Halbard, the Blacke-bill, or ſuch like weapons of weight, appertaining vnto guard or bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, are all one in fight, and haue aduantage againſt the two hand Sword, the Sword and Buckler, the Sword and Target, the Sword &amp; dagger, or the Rapier &amp; Poiniard.</p>
               <p>The ſhort ſtaffe or halfe Pike, Forreſt-bill, Partiſan, or Gleue, or ſuch like weapons of perfect length, haue the vantage againſt the Battel-axe, the Halbard, the Blacke-bill, the two hand ſword, the Sword and Target, and are too hard for two Swords and Daggers, or two Rapiers and Poiniards with Gantlets, and for the long ſtaffe and Morris Pike.</p>
               <p>The long Staffe, Morris Pike, or Iauelin, or ſuch like weapons aboue the perfect length, haue aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all maner of weapons, the ſhort ſtaffe, Welch hooke, Partiſan, or Gleue, or ſuch like weapons of van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage excepted: yet too weake for two Swords and Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or two Swords and Bucklers, or two Rapiers and Poiniards with Gantlets, becauſe they are too long to thruſt, ſtrike, and turne ſpeedily: and by reaſon of the large diſtance, one of the Sword and Dagger-men will get behind him.</p>
               <p>The Welch hooke or Forreſt bill, hath aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all maner of weapons whatſoeuer.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17956:23"/>
               <p>Yet vnderſtand, that in battels, and where varietie of weapons be, amongſt multitudes of men and horſes the Sword and Target, the two hand Sword, the Battel-axe, the Blacke-bill, and Halbard, are better weapons, and more dangerous in their offence and forces, then is the Sword and Buckler, ſhort ſtaffe, long ſtaffe, or Forreſt bill. The Sword and Target leadeth vpon Shot, and in troupes defendeth thruſts and blowes giuen by battel-axe, Halbards, Blacke-bill, or two hand ſwords, far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then can the Sword and Buckler.</p>
               <p>The Morris Pike defendeth the battell from both horſe and man, much better then can the ſhort ſtaffe, long ſtaffe, or Forreſt bill. Againe, the Battel-axe, the Halbard, the Blacke bill, the two hand ſword, and Sword &amp; Target, amongſt armed men and troopes, when men are come together, by reaſon of their weights, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and great forces, do much more offend the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, &amp; are then much better weapons, then is the ſhort ſtaffe, the long Staffe, or Forreſt bill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the inſufficiencie and diſaduantages of the Rapiers fight in Battell.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the ſingle Rapier, or Rapier &amp; Poiniard, they are imperfect &amp; inſufficient weapons: and eſpecially in the ſeruice of the Prince, when men ſhall ioyne together, what ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice can a ſouldier do with a Rapier, a chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh toy wherwith a man can do nothing but thruſt, nor that neither, by reaſon of the length, and in euerie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing when blowes are a dealing, for lacke of a hilt is in daunger to haue his hand or arme cut off, or his head
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17956:23"/> clouen. And for Wardes and Gripes, they haue none, neither can any of theſe fine Rapier men, for lacke of vſe, tell howe to ſtrike a ſound blow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the vantages and ſufficiencie of the short Sword fight in battell.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſhort Sword, and Sword and Dagger, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> are perfect good weapons, and eſpecially in ſeruice of the Prince. What a braue wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon is a ſhort ſharpe light Sword, to carie, to draw, to be nimble withall, to ſtrike, to cut, to thruſt both ſtrong and quicke. And what a goodly defence is a ſtrong ſingle hilt, when men are cluſtering and hurling together, eſpecially where varietie of weapons be, in their motions to defend the hand, head, face, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, from blowes, that ſhalbe giuen ſometimes with Swordes, ſometimes with two handed Swordes, battell Axe, Halbardes, or blacke Billes, and ſometimes men ſhalbe ſo neare together, that they ſhall haue no ſpace, ſcarce to vſe the blades of their Swordes belowe their waſtes, then their hilts (their handes being aloft) defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the blowes, their handes, armes, heads, faces, and bodies: then they lay on, hauing the vſe of blowes and Gripes, by force of their armes with their hilts, ſtrong blowes, at the head, face, armes, bodies, and ſhoulders, and manie times in hurling together, ſcope is giuen to turne downe their points, with violent thruſts at their faces, and bodies, by reaſon of the ſhortneſſe of their blades, to the mightie annoyance, diſcomfort, and great deſtruction of their enimies. One valiant man with a Sword in his hand, will doe better ſeruice, then ten <hi>Italians,</hi> or Italienated with the Rapiers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17956:24"/>
               <head>That all maner of double weapons, or weapons to be vſed with both handes, haue aduantage againſt the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Rapier or ſingle Sword, there is no queſtion to be made. That the Sword and Buckler hath the vantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sword and Dagger.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Dagger is an imperfect ward, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though borne out ſtraight, to make the Space narrow, whereby by a litle mouing of the hand, may be ſufficient to ſaue both ſides of the head, or to breake the thruſt from the face or body, yet for lacke of the circumference his hand will lie too high or too low, or too weake, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend both blow and thruſt: if he lye ſtraight with narrow ſpace, which is beſt to breake the thruſt, then he lieth too weake, and too lowe to defend his head from a ſtrong blow: if he lye high, that is ſtrong to defend his head, but then his ſpace wilbe too wide to breake the thruſt from his bodie. The Dagger ſerueth well at length to put by a thruſt, and at the halfe Sword to croſſe the Sword blade, to driue out the Agent, and put him in danger of his life, and ſafely in anie of theſe two actions to defend himſelfe. But the Buckler, by reaſon of his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference and weight, being well caried, defendeth ſafely in all times and places, whether it be at the point, halfe Sword, the head, bodie, and face, from all maner of blowes and thruſtes whatſoeuer, yet I haue heard ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie hold opinion, that the Sword and Dagger hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of the Sword and Buckler, at the Cloſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the length and point of the Dagger: and at the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17956:24"/> point of the Sword, they can better ſee to ward then with a Buckler. But I neuer knew anie, that wanne the Cloſe with the Dagger vpon the Sword and Buckler, but did wiſh himſelfe out againe: for diſtance being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, iudgement faileth, for lacke of time to iudge, and the eie is deceiued by the ſwift motion of the hand, and for lacke of true Space with the dagger hand, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe, for lacke of the circumference to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend both blow and thruſt, it is impoſſible for lacke of true Space in iuſt time, the agent hauing gotten the true place, to defend one thruſt or blow of an hundred. And it is moſt certaine, whoſoeuer cloſeth with Sword and Dagger, againſt the Sword and Buckler, is in great danger to be ſlaine. Likewiſe at the point within di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, if he ſtand to defend both blow and thruſt with his Dagger, for lacke of true ſpace and diſtance, if he had the beſt eye of anie man, and could ſee perfectly, which way the thruſt or blow commeth, and when it commeth, as it is not to be denied but he may, yet his ſpace being too large, it helpeth him nothing, becauſe one mans hand being as ſwift as another mans hand, both being within diſtance, he that ſtriketh or thruſteth, hurteth the warder: the reaſon is this: the Agent being in the firſt motion although in his offence, further to go then the warder to defend, yet the warders ſpace being too large, the blow or thruſt wilbe performed home, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the warder can come to the true place to defend himſelfe, and although the warder doe perfectly ſee the blow or thruſt comming, ſo ſhall he ſee his owne ward ſo farre from the true place of his defence, that although he doe at that inſtant time, plainly ſee the blow or thruſt comming, it ſhalbe impoſſible for him to recouer the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17956:25"/> true place of his ward, till he be wounded. But let the warder with the dagger ſay, that it is not true which I haue ſaid, for as he hath eies to behold the blow or thruſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, ſo hath he as good time to defend himſelf. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhal find himſelf deceiued to; this is the reaſon: the hand is the ſwifteſt motion, the foot is the ſloweſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtance the hand is tied to the motion of the feet, wherby the time of the hand is made as ſlow as the foot, becauſe thereby we redeeme euerie time loſt vpon his comming by the ſlow motion of the foot, &amp; haue time therby to iudge, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; how he can performe any actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whatſoeuer, and ſo haue we the time of the hand to the time of the feet. Now is the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his owne courſe more ſwifter then the foot or eye, therfore within diſtance the eye is deceiued, &amp; iudgement is loſt; and that is another cauſe that the warder with the dagger,<note place="margin">The eye is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ſwift motion of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> although he haue perfect eyes, is ſtil within diſtance deceiued. For proofe that the hand is more ſwifter then the eye, &amp; thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the eyes: let two ſtand within diſtance, &amp; let one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtand ſtill to defend himſelf, &amp; let the other floriſh &amp; falſe with his hand, and he ſhall continually with the ſwift motions of his hand, deceiue the eyes of him that ſtandeth watching to defend himſelfe, &amp; ſhal continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrike him in diuerſe places with his hand. Againe, take this for an example, that the eyes by ſwift motions are deceiued: turne a turne-wheele ſwift, &amp; you ſhall not be able to diſcerne with your beſt eies how many ſpokes be in the wheele, no nor whether there be any ſpokes at all, or whereof the wheele is made, and yet you ſee when the wheele ſtandeth ſtill there is a large diſtance betweene euerie ſpoke. He that will not beleeue that the ſwift mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hand in fight will deceiue the eye, ſhal ſtare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17956:25"/> with his eyes, &amp; feele himſelf ſoundly hurt, before he ſhall perfectly ſee how to defend himſelfe. So thoſe that truſt to their ſight, the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of a good eye, their great cunning, &amp; perfect wards of the daggers, that they can better ſee to ward then with a buckler, ſhall euer be deceiued. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be wounded, they ſay the Age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was a litle too quicke for them; ſometimes they ſay they bare their dagger a litle too low: ſometimes they are thruſt vnder the dagger, then they ſay, they bare it a litle too high: ſometimes a thruſt being ſtrongly made, they being ſoundly paid therewith, ſay, they were a litle too ſlow, &amp; ſometimes they be ſoundly paid with a thruſt, &amp; they thinke they were a litle too quick.<note place="margin">The Dagger is an imperfect ward.</note> So they that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe or thinke to be cunning in the dagger ward, are all the dayes of their liues learning, and are neuer taught.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the Sword and Buckler hath the vantage against the Sword and Target.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Sword &amp; Target together hath but two <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> fights; that is, the variable fight, &amp; the cloſe fight, for the cloſe fight, the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of his feet are too many to take againſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of skill hauing the Sword &amp; buckler, &amp; for the variable fight al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not ſo many in number, yet too many to win the place with his foot to ſtrike or thruſt home. The ſword &amp; buckler-man can out of his variable, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; garda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fight, come brauely off &amp; on, falſe and double, ſtrike &amp; thruſt home, &amp; make a true croſſe vpon euery occaſion at his pleaſure: if the Sword &amp; Target ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will flie to his garda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fight, the bredth of his Target will not ſuffer it, if to his open fight, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath the Sword &amp; Buckler man in effect the ſword and Buckler to the ſingle, for in that fight by reaſon of the bredth, the target can do litle good or none at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17956:26"/>
               <head>The short Staffe.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow for the vantage of the ſhort Staffe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sword and Buckler, Sword &amp; Target, two hand ſword, ſingle Sword, Sword and Dagger, or Rapier and Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, there is no great queſtion to be made in anie of theſe weapons: whenſoeuer anie blow or thruſt ſhall be ſtrongly made with the ſtaffe, they are euer in falſe place, in the cariage of the wards, for if at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe ſixe weapons he carie his ward high &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for his head, as of neceſſitie he muſt carie it verie high; otherwiſe it will be too weake to defend a blow being ſtrongly made at the head, then will his ſpace be too wide, in due time to breake the thruſt from his bodie. Againe, if he carie his ward lower, thereby to be in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall ſpace for readineſſe to breake both blow &amp; thruſt, then in that place his ward is too low, and too weake to defend the blow of the ſtaffe: for the blow being ſtrongly made at the head vpon that ward, will beate downe the ward and his head together, and put him in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life. And here is to be noted, that if he fight well, the ſtaffe-man neuer ſtriketh but at the head, and thruſteth preſently vnder at the body: and if a blow be firſt made, a thruſt followeth; &amp; if a thruſt be firſt made, a blow followeth; and in doing of any of them, the one breedeth the other: ſo that howſoeuer anie of theſe ſixe weapons ſhall carie his ward ſtrongly to defend the firſt, he ſhall be too farre in ſpace to defend the ſecond, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be blow or thruſt.</p>
               <p>Yet againe for the ſhort ſtaffe: the ſhort ſtaffe hath the vantage againſt the Battel-axe, blacke-bill, or Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17956:26"/> the ſhort ſtaffe hath the vantage, by reaſon of the nimbleneſſe and length: he will ſtrike and thruſt freely, and in better and ſwifter time then can the Battel-axe, Blacke-bill, or Halbard: and by reaſon of his iudgement, diſtance and time, fight ſafe. And this reſolue vpon, the ſhort ſtaffe is the beſt weapon againſt all maner of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, the Forreſt bill excepted.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſhort ſtaffe hath aduantage againſt two Swords and Daggers, or two Rapiers,<note place="margin">The ſhort ſtaffe or half Pike hath the aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt two ſword and dagger men, or two Rapiers. Poiniards, and Gantlets.</note> Poiniards and Gantlets, the reaſons and cauſes before are for the moſt part ſet downe already, the which being well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you ſhall plainely ſee, that whenſoeuer anie one of the Sword &amp; Dagger men, or Rapier and Poiniard men ſhall breake his diſtance, or ſuffer the Staffe man to breake his, that man which did firſt breake his diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or ſuffer the diſtance to be won againſt him, is preſently in danger of death. And this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not in reaſon be denied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the diſtance appertaining to the Staffe-man, either to keepe or breake, ſtandeth vpon the mouing of one large ſpace alwayes at the moſt, both for his offence or ſafety. The other two in the breach of their diſtance to offend the Staffe-man, haue alwayes foure paces at the leaſt therin they fall too great in number with their feet, and too ſhort in diſtance to offend the Staffe-man. Now there reſteth no more to be ſpoken of, but how the Staffe-man ſhall behaue himſelf to keepe that diſtance, that one of the Sword &amp; Dagger men get not behind him, while the other ſhal buſie him before: to do that is very eaſie, by reaſon of the ſmal nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of his feet, for by a verie ſmall turning of his feet, as it were in the Center point of a wheele, the other two to keepe their diſtance, are driuen to runne twentie foote for one, as it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17956:27"/> were vpon the vttermoſt part or circle of the wheele: all this while the Staffe-man is verie well. Then it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thus to paſſe, whether they both labour to get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, or one keepe directly before him whileſt the other get behind him, yet before that be brought to paſſe, they ſhal either be both before him or iuſt againſt both ſides of him: at which time ſoeuer the Staffe-man finding either of them within diſtance, he preſently in making of his play, ſlayeth with blow or thruſt one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or at the leaſt putteth him in great danger of his life. If the Staffe-man take his time, when they are both before him, that is to ſay, before they come to the half ring, iuſt againſt both ſides of the Staffe-man, then he that is neareſt within diſtance is ſlain by blow or thruſt, or put in great danger of his life. But if the Sword and Dagger men do keepe their diſtance vntill they come to the iuſt halfe ring right againſt the ſides of the Staffe-man, and then breake diſtance, that man that firſt brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth diſtance is ſlaine with blow or thruſt, or ſore hurt, and in great danger of death: and the Staffe-man in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that play at that inſtant, muſt turne with one large pace, the which he may eaſily do, before the other can get neare enough to offend him, by reaſon that he hath to make with his feet but one large pace, but the other hath at the leaſt three paces. But if the Sword and Dagger-men will in the time that they be before him, keep their diſtance in the time of their being vpon the middle part of the outſide of the circle, right againſt both ſides of him, &amp; will labor with all heed &amp; diligence to be both or one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behind him, that troubleth the Staffe-man nothing at all, for in that very time, when he findeth them paſt the middle part of the circle, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17956:27"/> turneth, by the which he ſhall naturally ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as it were in a triangle, and both the ſword and dagger-men, ſhall thereby ſtand both before him in true diſtance of three paces, from offending of him at the leaſt, as at the firſt they did. And take this for a true ground, there is no man able to ward a ſound blow with the Sword and Dagger, nor Rapier, Poinyard, and Gantlet, being ſtrongly made at the head, with the Staffe, and run in withall, the force of both handes is ſuch, being in his full motion and courſe, that although the other do carie his ward high and ſtrong with both handes, yet his feete being mouing from the ground, the great force of the blow will ſtrike him with his ward, and all downe flat to ground. But if he ſtand faſt with his feete, he may with both weapons together, ſtrongly defend his head from the blow, but then you are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inſtructed, the thruſt being preſently made, after the blow full at the bodie, it is impoſſible in due time to breake it, by reaſon of the largeneſſe of his ſpace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The short Staffe hath the vantage against the long ſtaffe, and Morris Pike, and the Forreſt bill againſt all maner of weapons.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reaſons are theſe. The ſhort Staffe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> hath the vantage of the long Staffe and Morris Pike in his ſtrength &amp; narrownes of ſpace in his foure wardes of defence. And the Forreſt bill hath the vantage of all maner of weapons in his ſtrength and narrownes of ſpace in his eight wardes of defence: and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Bill hath two wardes for one againſt the Staffe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17956:28"/> or Morris Pike, that is to ſay, foure with the Staffe, and foure with the head, and is more offenſiue then is the Staffe or Morris Pike: yet a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be made by the vnskilfull, concerning the fight between the long Staffe and the ſhort, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">A queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> in this ſort: Why ſhould not the long Staffe haue aduantage againſt ſhort Staffe, ſince that the long Staffe-man, being at libertie with his handes, may make his long Staffe both long and ſhort for his beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, when he ſhall thinke it good, and therefore when he ſhall find himſelfe ouermatched in the length of his Staffe, by the ſtrength of the ſhort Staffe, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſſe of ſpace in his foure wardes of defence, he can preſently by drawing backe of his Staffe in his handes, make his Staffe as ſhort as the others, and ſo be readie to fight with him at his owne length. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> To this I anſwere, that when the long Staffe-man is driuen there to lye, the length of his Staffe that will lye behind him, will hinder him to ſtrike, thruſt, ward, or goe backe in due time. Neither can he turne the contrarie end of his Staffe to keepe out the ſhort Staffe man from the Cloſe, nor ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to defend himſelfe at his comming in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againe of the vantages of weapons.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake this for a general rule, all long Staues, Morris Pikes, Forreſt bils, Iauelins, or ſuch like long weapons, of what ſort ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, being aboue the true lengthes, the ſhorteſt haue the aduantage, becauſe they can croſſe and vncroſſe in ſhorter time then can the longer: and all maner of ſhort weapons to be vſed with both handes, as ſtanes, and ſuch like, being vnder the perfect lengthes,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17956:28"/> the longeſt haue the aduantage, and all maner of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to be vſed with one hand, that are aboue the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect length of the ſingle Sword, the ſhorteſt haue the vantage, and all maner of weapons vnder the iuſt length of the ſhort Sword, as Fauchions, Skaines, or Hangers, Woodkniues, Daggers, and ſuch like ſhort weapons of imperfect lengthes, the longeſt haue the aduantage, becauſe the fight of theſe weapons conſiſt within the halfe or quarter Sword, wherein by the ſwift motions of their handes, their eyes are deceiued, and in thoſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, commonly for their handes lieth no defence. And if two ſhall fight with ſtaues or Swordes, or what wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons ſoeuer, the one of them hauing his weapon longer then the perfect length, and the other his weapon ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the perfect length, he that hath the longeſt hath the vantage, becauſe the ſhorteſt can make no true Croſſe in true time. The ſhort Staffe or halfe Pike, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt bill, Partiſan, or Gleue, or ſuch like weapons of perfect length, to be vſed with both handes, haue the aduantage againſt two Swordes and Daggers, or two Rapiers, Poiniardes, and Gantlets, and againſt all other weapons whatſoeuer, the Forreſt bill excepted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againe for the short Staffe or halfe Pike.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſhort Staffe is moſt commonly the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> beſt weapon of all other, although other weapons may be more offenſiue, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt manie weapons together, by reaſon of his nimbleneſſe and ſwift motions, and is not much inferiour to the Forreſt bill, although the Forreſt bill be more offenſiue, and hath more wardes, becauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17956:29"/> the Staffe is verie vncertaine, but the Bill is a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine marke, by reaſon of the breadth of the head, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as the Bill hath aduantage in his wardes in the head, ſo therefore hath the Staffe the like defence, or rather more, to play vpon the head of the Bill, not onely to make a perfect good ward, but thereby, the rather to caſt the Bill out of the right line, whereby the Staffe-man may thruſt ſafe, and endanger the Bill-man: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe therein he is the firſt mouer, wherin there is great vantage, both in time and force. And if the Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be not very skilfull (all vantages and diſaduantages of both ſides conſidered,) the ſhort Staffe will proue the better weapon.<note place="margin">Note this.</note> Laſtly note this, that long Staues, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Pikes, and ſuch like weapons of imperfect lengthes, being to be vſed with both hands, notwithſtanding their imperfect lengthes, are perfect weapons to be vſed, the one againſt the other, and their fightes therein perfect, becauſe in drawing of them backe betwixt their handes, their motions are ſwifter backewardes, then is the time of the Agents feet forwardes, by the which all their loſt times are redeemed: therefore theſe weapons in their fightes, the one againſt the other are perfect. And theſe weapons in the night are the beſt weapons of all other, and haue great aduantage againſt the forreſt Bill, ſhort Staffe, or anie maner of ſhort weapons whatſoeuer: for theſe cauſes, they boldly make home their fightes, and if neede be againſt deſperate men, that will venture themſelues to run in, they redeeme their loſt times. But the other with ſhorter weapons for lacke of light, can make no true defence. Thus endeth the vantages of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17956:29"/>
               <head>Queſtions and anſwers betweene the Scholler and the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, of the vantages and diſaduantages betweene a tall man, and a man of meane ſtature, hauing both the perfect knowledge in their weapons.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho hath the aduantage in fight, of a tall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> man, or a man of meane ſtature?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maiſter.</speaker>
                  <p>The tall man hath the vantage, for theſe cauſes: his reach being longer, and weapon vnto his ſtature accordingly,<note place="margin">Tall men haue the vantage againſt men of meane ſtature.</note> he hath thereby a ſhorter courſe with his feet to win the true place, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the ſwift motion of his hand, he may ſtrike or thruſt home: in the which time a man of meane ſtature cannot reach him, &amp; by his large pace, in his true pace in his regreſſion further, ſetteth himſelf out of all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; theſe are the vantages that a tall man hath againſt anie man of ſhorter reach then himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
                  <p>What vantage hath a man of meane ſtature againſt a tall man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maiſter.</speaker>
                  <p>He hath none: becauſe the true times in fight, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions accordingly, are to be obſerued and done, as well by a tall man, as by a man of meane ſtature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then if this be true, that tall men haue the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of meane ſtature, it ſhold ſeeme in fight
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17956:30"/> there is no perfection, other then this, when men of like ſtature, reach, &amp; length of weapon, ſhall fight together, the which will ſeldome or neuer happen, but either in the length of their weapons, ſtatures or reaches (if their ſwords ſhould be of iuſt length) ſome difference moſt commonly there will be in their reaches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maiſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes verily, the tall man hath ſtill the vantage, and yet the fight is perfect, although the men that ſhall happen to fight, ſhall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vnequall in their ſtatures, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or lengths of their weapons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
                  <p>That can I hardly beleeue, vnleſſe you can tell me by Art how to auoid or ſafely defend my ſelfe, being but a man of meane ſtature, againſt a tall man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maiſter.</speaker>
                  <p>I will tell you: there belongeth vnto this Art of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence onely to be vſed with the feet, progreſſion, regreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, trauerſing, and treading of grounds: in any of theſe you playing the part of the Patient, or Patient Agent, your feete are ſwifter in their motions then are the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, becauſe his weight and number of his feet in his comming to win the true place to ſtrike or thruſt home, are greater then yours, and therefore the true time is yours to auoid him, or ſafely to defend your ſelfe: ſo the Art is ſtill true, and the tall man hath ſtill the vantage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I am not fully ſatisfied herein, becauſe you tell me ſtill that the tall man hath the vantage, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you ſay the Art is true, wherein then hath the tall man the vantage, when by your Art you can defend your ſelfe againſt him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17956:30"/>
                  <speaker>Maiſter.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſatisfie you therein thus. The tall man hath the vantage, he can maintaine his fight, both by nature and Art, with more eaſe then can the man of meane ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe the man of meane ſtature hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a further courſe with his feete to paſſe to the place, wherein he may ſtrike or thruſt home, and in winning of that place, is driuen by Art to come garded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his wards to defend himſelfe, becauſe in the time of his comming, the tall man may both naturally or artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſtrike or thruſt home, in the which time, if the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of meane ſtature ſhould faile in the leaſt iote of his Art, he ſhould be in great daunger of death or hurt. But the tall man can naturally and ſafely come to the true place open, without any artificiall wards at all, and therein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo endanger the other,<note place="margin">Foure inuincible aduantages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in a tall man againſt a man of meane ſtature. Long reach. Short courſe. Length of weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Large pace.</note> or driue him ſtill to trauerſe his ground, with all the artificiall skill that he hath to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelfe; and all this the tall man doth by reaſon of his length of weapon, large pace, ſhort courſe, and long reach, with great ſafetie, pleaſure and eaſe. And for thoſe cauſes the tall man hath ſtill the vantage of men of meane ſtature, and yet notwitſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the noble Science of Defence moſt perfect and good.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the long ſingle Rapier fight betweene valiant men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing both skill, he that it the beſt wraſtler, or if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them can wraſtle, the ſtrongeſt man moſt commonly killeth the other, or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him at his mercie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen two valiant men of skill at ſingle Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> do fight, one or both of them moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſtanding vpon their ſtrength or skill in wraſtling, will preſently ſeeke to run into
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17956:31"/> the cloſe; but hauing both skill, not without ſpeciall care of their gard or croſſe, the which they may ſafely do, by reaſon of the length of their Rapiers: but hapning both of one mind, the rather do bring themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: that being done, no skil with Rapiers auaileth, they preſently grapple faſt their hilts, wriſts, armes, bodies or neckes, as in luſtring, wraſtling, or ſtriuing together, they may beſt find for their aduantages: wherby it moſt commonly falleth out, that he that is the beſt wraſtler, or ſtrongeſt man (if neither of them can wraſtle) ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth, wreſting by ſtrength, or fine skill in wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the Rapier from his aduerſarie, or caſting him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, either to the ground, or to ſuch diſtance, that he may by reaſon therof, vſe the edge or point of his rapier, to ſtrike or thruſt him, leauing him dead or aliue at his mercie. But if but one of theſe valiant men ſhall ſeeke to run into the cloſe, and that the other ſhall vſe his skill in trauerſing of his ground, or otherwiſe by ſtanding vpon his gard or <hi>Stocata</hi> ward, to take all maner of adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, yet all auaileth him not, becauſe the Rapiers being long, the croſſing of the blades cannot be auoided: that being made, the oppreſſor runneth faſter forwards then can the defendant backwards, and ſo are brought together, as in the firſt aſſault they were, &amp; euerie action therein accordingly performed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Rapier and Poiniard fight betwixt valiant men, hauing both skill.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F two valiant men do fight at Rapier and Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard hauing both skill, one or both of them will preſently preſſe hard to winne the place, wherein in his iudgement he may thruſt home. If both
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17956:31"/> be of one mind, the time is doubled in winning the ſame: whereby it commeth to paſſe, that then he that firſt thruſteth, endangereth, killeth or hurteth the other: and if they both thruſt together, as they may do by the equall time of their feet, then they are moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both ſlaine, or both hurt. And this is well knowne vnto all men of skill, that the place being once gotten, there is neither iudgement, ſpace, pace, nor time, either by wards with their Rapier blades, or by breaking with their Poiniards, or flying backe, that can preſerue or defend them. But if but one of them will ſeeke to win by paſſage, hard preſſing, or otherwiſe the place, wherin in his judgement he may thruſt home, it is impoſſible for the other to denie him the ſame, becauſe the length of the Rapiers winneth him the croſſe; the croſſe being taken, the place is had; the place being had, he that firſt thruſteth, firſt ſpeedeth: if both thruſt together, they are both in danger: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſently followeth (vnleſſe it pleaſe God otherwiſe to haue it) the ſtabs with their daggers, wherein there lieth no defence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the long Rapier &amp; Poiniard-fight betweene two valiant men, the one hauing skil, the other none: that he that hath no skill hath the vantage.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen two valiant men ſhal fight with lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> Rapiers and Poiniards, the one hauing skill, and the other none, he that hath no skill moſt commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly proueth himſelf the better ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for theſe cauſes or reaſons fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Firſt the skilfull man as knowing the other to haue no skill, or finding it to be ſo by his ſhape or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17956:32"/> maner of comming towardes him, will preſently yeeld to take the aduantage of his comming, or elſe with all ſpeed put himſelfe into his ſhort ward, to be readie at his comming to make out a ſtrong <hi>Stocata</hi> (as the <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> call it) the other knowing his imperfection in fight, aſſureth himſelfe there can be no great good for him to ſtand long out at the point, preſently redoubleth or reuiueth his ſpirits with perfect reſolution, to make ſhort worke, couragiouſly with ſome offenſiue action, ſuch as nature ſhall beſt yeeld vnto him, flieth in with all force and agilitie, the skilfull man ſtandeth watching to take ſuch aduantages as his ſchoolemaiſter hath taught him, in the which time, manie times it falleth out, he is taught a new time, euen by an vnskilfull man that neuer fought before, is ſore hurt or ſlaine: and if it happen they both miſſe in their offenſiue actions, then by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof, and of the imperfect length of their Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers, they come to ſtabbing with their Poiniards, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there lyeth no defence, becauſe diſtance being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, iudgement faileth, time is loſt, and their eies (by the ſwift motions of their handes) are deceiued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the long ſingle Rapier, or Rapier and Poiniard-fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two vnskilfull men being valiant.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen two vnskilfull men (being valiant) ſhall fight with long ſingle Rapiers, there is leſſe danger in that kind of fight, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their diſtance in conuenient length, waight, and vnweildineſſe, then is with ſhort Rapiers, whereby it commeth to paſſe, that what hurt ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be done, if anie with the edge or point of their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17956:32"/> Rapiers is done in a moment, and preſently will grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and wraſtle together, wherin moſt commonly the ſtrongeſt or beſt Wraſtler ouercommeth, and the like fight falleth out betweene them, at the long Rapier and Poiniard, but much more deadly, becauſe in ſtead of Cloſe and Wraſtling, they fall moſt commonly to ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing with their Poiniardes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the imperfection and inſufficiencie of Rapiers in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, of what length ſoeuer they be.</head>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F two fight with long Rapiers,<note place="margin">
                     <p>If they ſtand v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon breaking with their Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, he that firſt winneth the place, and thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth home, hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the other for lacke of the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: if both thruſt together, they are both ſped, becauſe their Spaces of Defence are too wide to anſwere the time of the hand, and by the ſwift motion thereof, the eye in that diſtance is by the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
                     <p>The feete in their courſe, but not in the firſt motion, alwaies note for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of great errours.</p>
                  </note> vpon euerie Croſſe made within the halfe Rapier, if they haue Poiniardes, they moſt commonly ſtabbe each other, which cannot be auoided, becauſe the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers being long, the Croſſe cannot be vndone of either ſide, without going backe with their feete, the which likewiſe in due time cannot be done, becauſe the hand is more ſwifter then the feete, and the feete more ſwifter in their courſe forwardes then backwardes, neither can the Croſſe be preuented, becauſe the point of neceſſitie lyeth too farre off in his offence, or elſe within compaſſe of the true time of the hand and bodie, by reaſon of his imperfect length, and ſo by the like reaſons, if two fight with long ſingle Rapiers, vpon euerie Croſſe made therewith, within the halfe Rapier, the Cloſe cannot be auoided, wherby it commeth to paſſe, moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the ſtrongeſt man or beſt Wraſtler, ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. Now if two do fight with ſhort Rapiers, or Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers of conuenient length, ſuch Rapiers be inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and inſufficient alſo for lacke of an hilt to defend the hand and head from the blow; for no eie (in making a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17956:33"/> perfect ward for the head, to defend a blow, can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne to take the ſame within three or foure inches, wherby it may as well and as often fall vpon the hand, as vpon the blade of the Rapier. Againe, the hilt as well ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to defend the head as the hand, and is a more ſure and ſtrong ward, then is the blade of the Rapier. And further, vnderſtand this for truth, that in gardant and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fight, the hand without an hilt lieth open to moſt blowes that ſhalbe ſtroken by the Agent, out of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant or open fight, becauſe in the true cariage of the gardant fight, the hand muſt lie aboue the head, in ſuch ſtraightnes and narrownes of ſpace, that which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Agent ſhall ſtrike or thruſt at the head, face, or bodie, the remouing of two or foure inches ſhall ſaue all. And now ſome what more for the ſhortneſſe or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient length of Rapiers.</p>
               <p>Rapiers hauing no hilts to defend the head, the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier-man is driuen of neceſſitie to lie at the variable fight or low ward, and being there he can neither defend in due time, head, face, nor bodie from the blowes or thruſtes of him, that ſhall fight out of the gardant or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fight, but is continually in great danger of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, for theſe cauſes following. Firſt, becauſe his ſpace is too wide to defend his head from blow or thruſt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly his Pace ſtanding vpon that fight, wilbe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie too great or too narrow: if too narrow, too weak: if too large, his weight and number of his feet, are too great to endanger him, that is vpon his gardant or open fight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:17956:33"/>
               <head>Of the imperfection and inſufficiencie of the fight of the ſingle Rapier, Rapier and Poiniard, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier and Buckler, Rapier and Cloke, and Rapier and Gloue of maile.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Rapier fight, whether it be ſingle or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> with Poiniard, Buckler, cloke, or gloue of male, is ſtill by reaſon of the inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie or imperfection of the Rapier, an imperfect fight: vnperfect inſtruments can make no perfect muſicke, neither can vnperfect weapons make perfect fight: let the men that handle them haue all the knowledge that may be in all maner of weapons, yea the full height, or perfection, and true habite by his great labour and induſtry, euen as it were naturally effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in him, yet if the weapons that they ſhall fight withall be imperfect or inſufficient to performe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer appertaineth vnto true fight, as concerning the perfection of their ſafetie, it auaileth them nothing. What ſhall we then ſay for the Rapier? Is the Rapier an imperfect or inſufficient weapon to perfourme whatſoeuer appertaineth vnto the true fight? Yea: Wherefore? Becauſe vnto the true fight there apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth foure fights, Gardant fight, Open fight, Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fight, and Cloſe fight: without all foure of theſe fights it is impoſſible to fight ſafe: but the Rapier for lacke of an hilt is an vnperfect weapon, and therefore inſufficient to fight ſafe vpon theſe foure fights, the reaſons are alreadie ſet downe in the Paradoxe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but it is inferred to looſe the benefit of two of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17956:34"/> beſt fights, gardant and open fight, and to flie from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and truſt only vnto variable fight, and cloſe fight. Now hauing proued through the imperfection or inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Rapier, the imperfection of the Rapier fight, it remaineth that I ſpeake of the reſt of the weapons, or inſtruments appertaining vnto Rapier fight.</p>
               <p>The Rapier and Poiniard fight, the Rapier &amp; Buckler fight, the Rapier and cloke fight, &amp; the Rapier &amp; gloue of male fight: all theſe fights by reaſon of the imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Rapier, and Rapier fight, are all alſo imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect fights: and for proofe of the vncertaintie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities of ſafetie in any of theſe fights, thus it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. Theſe fights depend altogether vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> variable fight and cloſe fight: in anie of theſe fights it is impoſſible in true ſpace of Offence to keepe the blades of their Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers from croſſing, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breaking with the Poiniards, buckler, cloke, or breaking or catching with the gloue of male; becauſe in anie of theſe two fights, the Agent hath ſtill in true ſpace the blade of the Patients Rapier to worke vpon. Theſe things by letters cannot be made more plaine, neither is it vnknowne to the skilfull, or in fight by anie meanes to be auoided, the weapon being too farre in true ſpace to be wrought vpon, the place cannot be denied, do the patient Agent what he can for his life to the contrarie, either by blowes, thruſts, falſing, or doubling of thruſts, going backe, indirections, or turnings of the body, or what elſe ſoeuer may in the higheſt touch of wit or ſtrength, or agilitie of bodie be deuiſed or done, to keepe out the Agent: but ſtill the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent by narrowneſſe of ſpace bringeth himſelf by ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gard to the place, where being brought, it is as impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fight ſafe, as as it is for two deſperate men ſet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17956:34"/> being both blind, becauſe in the the true place (won in Rapier or variable fight) their eyes by the ſwift mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their hands are deceiued, the croſſes in that fight are falſe, their diſtance, iudgements and times are loſt, either to offend in ſafetie, or ſafely to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and theſe reaſons, rules, or grounds of the feates of armes are infallible and inuincible.</p>
               <p>Now, ô you Italian teachers of Defence, where are your <hi>Stocatas, Imbrocatas, Mandritas, Puntas,</hi> &amp; <hi>Puynta reuerſas, Stramiſons, Paſſatas, Carricados, Amazzas,</hi> &amp; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cartatas,</hi> &amp; playing with your bodies, remouing with your feet a litle aſide, circle wiſe winding of your bodies, making of three times with your feet together, marking with one eye the motion of the aduerſary, &amp; with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eye the adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage of thruſting? What is become of all theſe iugling gambalds, Apiſh deuiſes, with all the reſt of your ſquint-eyed trickes? when as through your deepe ſtudies, long practiſes, &amp; apt bodies, both ſtrong &amp; agilious, you haue attained to the height of all theſe things. What then auaileth it you, when you ſhal come to fight for your liues with a man of skill, you ſhall haue neither time, nor place, in due time to performe any one of them. Nor gardant nor open fight ſafely to keep out a man of skill, a man of no skill, or ſcholler of your owne teaching, from the true place, the place of ſafetie, the place of vncertaintie or miſchiefe, the place of wounds or death, but are there inforced to ſtand in that miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, vncertaine, dangerous, and moſt deadly place, as two men hauing loſt in part their chiefeſt ſences, moſt furiouſly with their rapiers or poiniards, wounding or ſlaying each other.</p>
               <p>Thus endeth the imperfect fights of the rapier with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17956:35"/> all maner of weapons or inſtruments thereto appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with their imperfections, through the true grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and rules of the Art of armes, truly diſplayed &amp; brought to light.</p>
               <closer>All laud be vnto the Almighty God.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the reaſons vſed by the Italian Fencers in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the vſe of the Rapier and Poiniard, becauſe it maketh peace, maketh againſt themſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bin commonly held, that ſince the Italians haue taught the Rapier fight, by reaſon of the dangerous vſe therof, it hath bred great ciuilitie amongſt our Engliſh nation,<note place="margin">There are few frayes, but more valiant Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlaine now then were the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> they will not now giue the lye, nor with ſuch foule ſpeeches abuſe themſelues, therefore there are fewer frayes in theſe times then were wont to be: it cannot be denied but this is true, that we are more circumſpect of our words, and more fearefull to fight, then heretofore we haue bene. But whereof commeth it? Is it from this, that the Rapier maketh peace in our minds; or from hence, that it is not ſo ſufficient defence for our bodies in our fight? He that will fight when he is armed, will not fight when he is naked: is it therefore good to go naked to keepe peace? he that would fight with his Sword and Buckler, or Sword and Dagger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weapons of true defence, will not fight with his Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier and Poiniard, wherein no true defence or fight is perfect: are theſe inſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therfore the better, becauſe not being ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs in fight, they force vs vnto peace? What elſe is it, but to ſay, it is good for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17956:35"/> ſubiects to be poore, that they may not go to law: or to lacke emunition, that they may not fight, nor go to the warres: and to conclude, what more followeth through the imperfect workes of theſe <hi>Italian</hi> peacemakers? They haue made many a ſtrong man in his fight weake, many a valiant man fearefull, manie a worthie man truſting to their imperfect fight, hath bene ſlaine, and manie of our deſperate boyes and young youthes, to become in that Rapier-fight, as good men as <hi>England</hi> yeeldeth, and the talleſt men in this land, in that fight as verie boyes as they and no better. This good haue the <hi>Italian</hi> teachers of Offence done vs, they haue transformed our boyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, and our men into boyes, our ſtrong men into weakeneſſe, our valiant men doubtfull, and manie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men reſoluing themſelues vpon their falſe reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, haue moſt wilfully in the field, with their Rapiers ended their liues. And laſtly, haue left to remaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs after their deathes, theſe inconueniences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, falſe Fence-bookes, imperfect weapons, falſe fightes, and euill cuſtomes, whereby for lacke of vſe and practiſe in perfect weapons and true fight, we are diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the ſeruice of our Prince, defence of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and ſafetie of our liues in priuate fight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the short Sword hath the aduantage againſt the long Sword or long Rapier.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas for the moſt part opinions are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> generally holden, that the long Sword, or long Rapier, hath the vantage in fight againſt the ſhort Sword, which the <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> teachers of Defence, by their falſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17956:36"/> haue brought vs to beleeue. I haue thought good that the truth may appeare which hath the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to adde my helpe vnto the reaſons they vſe in their owne behalfe, for that yet I could neuer heare them make a ſound reaſon for the ſame. Theſe are the reaſons. Firſt with my long Rapier,<note place="margin">Theſe reaſons are vſed by the Italians.</note> I will put my ſelfe into my gard or <hi>Stocata,</hi> holding my hilt backe by the outſide of my right thigh, keeping in ſhort the point of my Rapier, ſo as he that hath the ſhort Sword, ſhall not be able to reach the point of my Rapier, to make his ward or Croſſe with his Dagger, Buckler, Sword, or Cloke, without ſtepping in of his foote, the which time is too long to anſwere the time of the hand, by reaſon of my diſtance. I can there ſtand ſafe without danger of blow or thruſt, playing the Patients part: if you ſtrike or thruſt you do it too ſhort, by reaſon of my diſtance: if you ſeek to come nearer, you muſt do it with the time of your foote, in the which time I may ſafely thruſt home: if in that diſtance you breake it not, you are ſlaine: if you do breake it, yet you do me no harme, by reaſon of my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and I may ſtand faſt and thruſt againe; or flie backe at my pleaſure: ſo haue you put your ſelfe in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of your life, and hauing hardly eſcaped, are driuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to begin a new bought, as at the firſt you did. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if I pleaſe, I can be the oppreſſour, keeping the ſame gard, and my point in ſhort as I did before, and preſſing ſtrongly by putting in by litle and litle of my feete, vntill the place with my foote be gotten, wherein (in my iudgement) I may thruſt home, the which I may boldly and ſafely do, without reſpect of anie ward at all, by reaſon of my diſtance, in which time of my comming he muſt ſtrike, thruſt, ward, or go backe: if he go backe,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17956:36"/> it is a great diſgrace: if he ſtrike or thruſt, it is too ſhort: if he ſtand to defend, the place being alreadie gotten, where I may thruſt home, the thruſt being verie quicke &amp; ſtrongly made, ſuch is the force and ſwiftneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that it is impoſſible by nature or art, for anie man to breake one thruſt of an hundred. Theſe reaſons in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion may ſuffice to confirme the wiſe, that there is no queſtion to be made, but that the long Rapier hath the aduantage againſt the ſhort Sword.</p>
               <p>Sir you hue pretily handled your diſcourſe,<note place="margin">A confutation of the Italians rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vantages of the long Rapier againſt the ſhort Sword, eſpecially at the firſt ſhew, and according to common ſence, but for the ſubſtance and truth of the true fight, you haue ſaid nothing, becauſe for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of anie of your allegations, you haue neither true Pace, Place, Time, nor Space: theſe are the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Your Pace of neceſſitie muſt be too large, becauſe otherwiſe you cannot keepe ſafe the point of your long Rapier, from the Croſſe of the ſhort Sword, vnleſſe you will with a narrow Pace keepe backe your hilt ſo farre, that the ſpace of your offence wilbe too large or too long in diſtance, and your bodie vnapt to moue and to thruſt ſtrong and quicke in due time, nor aptly to keepe your diſtance, to win the place with your feete, to thruſt home. So now you may plainely ſee, if you have skill in the art or ſcience of Defence, that to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme anie thing which you haue alleadged, you haue neither true Pace, Place, time nor Space. But if you will ſtand vpon the largeneſſe of your Pace, to keepe backe or ſaue the point of your long Rapier from the ward or Croſſe of the ſhort Sword, or vpon your <hi>Paſſatos,</hi> in all theſe you haue great diſaduantages: and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17956:37"/> theſe are my reaſons: Your number will be too great, as thus: whenſoeuer you meane out of your large pace to thruſt home, you muſt of neceſſitie make foure times with your feet, and one with your hand, or two times with your feet, and one with your hand at the leaſt: and whenſoeuer you make any of your paſſages, the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of your feet are greater then the greateſt of any of theſe times done out of the large pace: but the patient with his ſhort ſword, to auoyd you, or diſappoint you of your thruſt, hath but one time with his foot, at or before the which time, as he in his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhall find you in your motion, hath by the ſlow and great number of your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or times, ſufficient time ſafely out of all danger to make himſelfe readie to take his croſſe with his ſhort ſword. Now Sir, whether you thruſt or not thruſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you play the part of an Agent, or Patient, it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth you nothing, for he that hath the ſhort ſword hath foure times or motions againſt the long Rapier, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, bent, ſpent, lying ſpent, and drawing backe, in all maner of fights theſe are to be obſerued both by the Patient and Agent. Now note, he that hath the long Rapier muſt of neceſſitie play vpon one of theſe foure motions, or be Patient, which ſoeuer he ſhall do, he is ſtill in great danger of the croſſe of the ſhort ſword, becauſe if he be Agent, his number is too great, he falleth into one of the foure motions, the Patient with his ſhort ſword, hauing but the time of the hand, or ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; foot, ſafely vpon theſe actions or times taketh his croſſe with the ſhort Sword: that being done, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vncroſſeth and ſtriketh or thruſteth at his pleaſure him that hath the long Rapier, in the head, face, or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Now here is againe to be noted, that when the croſſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17956:37"/> is made, if he that hath the long Rapier ſtand faſt, he is wounded preſently in the vncroſſing of the ſhort ſword, if he ſtep or leape backe to ſaue himſelfe, yet the time of the hand being ſwifter then the time of the foot, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh him, with blow or thruſt in the arme, hand, head, face and bodie. Now if he that hath the long Rapier will be patient &amp; make no play, but lie ſtill watching to make his thruſt or <hi>Stocata</hi> iuſt in the comming or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Agents feete with his ſhort ſword, then he hath as great diſaduantage as he had when he was Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, becauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Agent with his ſhort Sword hath but hand and foot to make his croſſe: which is moſt ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be done in that time, which we call Bent, and is as impoſſible for the Rapier-man to preuent, as it is for an vnskilfull to ſtrike or thruſt iuſt together with a man of skill. Then thus I conclude, that he that fighteth with a long Rapier, againſt him that fighteth with a ſhort Sword, can do nothing in due time to defend himſelfe, or hurt the other, but is ſtill in daunger of his life, or at the mercie of him that hath the ſhort Sword, or elſe hath no ſafe way to helpe himſelfe,<note place="margin">Cobs Trauerſe.</note> but onely <hi>Cobs</hi> Trauerſe. This <hi>Cob</hi> was a great quareller, and did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in great brauerie to giue foule words to his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and would not refuſe to go into the field to fight with any man, and when he came into the field, would draw his Sword to fight, for he was ſure by the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Trauerſe, not to be hurt by anie man: for at anie time finding himſelfe ouermatched would ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly turne his backe and runne away with ſuch ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it was thought a good horſe would ſcarce take him. And this when I was a young man, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie much ſpoken of by many Gentlemen of the Innes of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17956:38"/> the Court, and was called <hi>Cobs</hi> Trauerſe and thoſe that had ſeene anie go backe too faſt in his fight, would ſay, he did tread <hi>Cobs</hi> Trauerſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>George Siluer his militarie riddle, truly ſet downe betweene the Perfection and Imperfection of fight: containing the handling of the foure fights: wherein true conſiſteth the whole ſumme and full perfection of the true fight, with all maner of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, with an inuicible concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ardant fight ſtayeth, putteth backe, or beateth gardant fight.</p>
               <p>Open fight ſtayeth, putteth backe, or beateth open fight.</p>
               <p>Variable fight anſwereth variable fight in the firſt diſtance, and not otherwiſe, except it be with the perfect length againſt the imperfect.</p>
               <p>Cloſe fight is beaten by gardant fight.</p>
               <p>Variable cloſe &amp; gardant fight, beateth gardant fight, open fight, variable fight, and cloſe fight.</p>
               <p>Gardant fight in the imperfection of the Agent or Patient, winneth the halfe ſword, and preuenteth the cloſe, and whoſoeuer firſt ventureth the cloſe, looſeth it, and is in great danger of death, and not poſſible to eſcape or get out againe without great hurt.</p>
               <p>There attendeth moſt diligently vpon theſe foure fights foure offenſiue actions, which we call certaine, vncertaine, firſt, before, iuſt, and afterwards: they are to be performed through iudgement, time, meaſure, number and waight, by which all maner of blowes,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17956:38"/> thruſts, falſes, doubles, or ſlips, are preuented, or moſt ſafely defended. And thus endeth my riddle.</p>
               <p>Now followeth the concluſion, that whoſoeuer ſhall thinke or find himſelfe in his fight too weake for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, or Patient Agent, and therefore, or by reaſon of his drunkenneſſe, or vnreaſonable deſperateneſſe ſhall preſe within the halfe Sword, or deſerately runne in of purpoſe to giue hurt, or at leaſt for taking of one hurt, to giue another, ſhall moſt aſſuredly be in great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death or wounds, and the other ſhall ſtill be ſafe and go free.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Veritas vincit.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="note">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:17956:39"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE NOTE OF THREE <hi>ITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Teachers of Offence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I write not this to diſgrace the dead, but to ſhew their impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t boldneſſe and inſufficiency in performance of their profeſſion when they were liuing: that from henceforth this briefe note may be a remembrance and warning to beware of had I wiſt.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were three Italian Teachers of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in my time. The firſt was <hi>Signior Rocko:</hi> the ſecond was <hi>Ieronimo,</hi> that was <hi>Signior Rocko</hi> his boy, that taught Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in the <hi>Blacke-Fryers,</hi> as Vſher for his maiſter in ſteed of a man. The third was <hi>Vincentio.</hi> This <hi>Signior Rocko</hi> came into <hi>England</hi> about ſome thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares paſt: he taught the Noblemen &amp; Gentlemen of the Court; he cauſed ſome of them to weare leaden ſoales in their ſhoes, the better to bring them to nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of feet in their fight. He disburſed a great ſumme of mony for the leaſe of a faire houſe in <hi>VVarwicke</hi> lane, which he called his Colledge, for he thought it great diſgrace for him to keepe a Fence-ſchoole, he being then thought to be the onely famous Maiſter of the Art of armes in the whole world. He cauſed to be fairely drawne and ſet round about his Schoole all the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens and Gentlemens armes that were his Schollers, and hanging right vnder their armes their Rapiers, dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, gloues of male and gantlets. Alſo, he had benches and ſtooles, the roome being verie large, for Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſit round about his Schoole to behold his teaching. He taught none commonly vnder twentie, fortie, fifty, or an hundred pounds. And becauſe all things ſhould be verie neceſſary for the Nobleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he had
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17956:39"/> in his ſchoole a large ſquare table, with a greene car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, done round with a verie brode rich fringe of gold, alwaies ſtanding vpon it a verie faire Standiſh couered with Crimſon Veluet, with inke, pens, pin-duſt, and ſealing waxe, and quiers of verie excellent fine paper gilded, readie for the Noblemen &amp; Gentlemen (vpon occaſion) to write their letters, being then deſirous to follow their fight, to ſend their men to diſpatch their buſineſſe. And to know how the time paſſed, he had in one corner of his ſchoole a Clocke, with a verie faire large Diall, he had within that ſchoole, a roome the which was called his priuie ſchoole, with manie wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons therein, where he did teach his ſchollers his ſecret fight, after he had perfectly taught them their rules. He was verie much beloued in the Court.</p>
            <p>There was one <hi>Auſten Bagger,</hi> a verie tall gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his handes, not ſtanding much vpon his skill, but carying the valiant hart of an Engliſhman, vpon a time being merrie amongſt his friendes, ſaid he would go fight with <hi>Signior Rocco,</hi> preſently went to <hi>Signior Rocco</hi> his houſe in the <hi>Blackefriers,</hi> and called to him in this maner: <hi>Signior Rocco,</hi> thou that art thought to be the onely cunning man in the world with thy weapon, thou that takeſt vpon thee to hit anie Engliſhman with a thruſt vpon anie button, thou that takeſt vpon thee to come ouer the ſeas, to teach the valiant Noblemen and Gentlemen of <hi>England</hi> to fight, thou cowardly fellow come out of thy houſe if thou dare for thy life, I am come to fight with thee. <hi>Signior Rocco</hi> looking out at a window, perceiuing him in the ſtreet to ſtand readie with his Sword and Buckler, with his two hand Sword drawne, with all ſpeed ran into the ſtreet, and manfully
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17956:40"/> let flie at <hi>Auſten Bagger,</hi> who moſt brauely defended himſelfe, and preſently cloſed with him, and ſtroke vp his heeles, and cut him ouer the breech, and trode vpon him, and moſt grieuouſly hurt him vnder his feet: yet in the end <hi>Auſten</hi> of his good nature gaue him his life, and there left him. This was the firſt and laſt fight that euer <hi>Signior Rocco</hi> made, ſauing once at Queene Hith he drew his Rapier vpon a waterman, where he was throughly beaten with Oares and Stretchers, but the oddes of their weapons were as great againſt his Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier, as was his two hand Sword againſt <hi>Auſten Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> Sword and Buckler, therefore for that fray he was to be excuſed.</p>
            <p>Then came in <hi>Vincentio</hi> and <hi>Ieronimo,</hi> they taught Rapier-fight at the Court, at <hi>London,</hi> and in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, by the ſpace of ſeauen or eight yeares or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts. Theſe two <hi>Italian</hi> Fencers, eſpecially <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentio,</hi> ſaid that Engliſhmen were ſtrong men, but had no cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and they would go backe too much in their fight, which was great diſgrace vnto them. Vpon theſe words of diſgrace againſt Engliſhmen, my brother <hi>Toby Siluer</hi> and my ſelfe, made challenge againſt them both, to play with them at the ſingle Rapier, Rapier and Dagger, the ſingle Dagger, the ſingle Sword, the Sword and Target, the Sword and Buckler, &amp; two hand Sword, the Staffe, battell Axe, and Morris Pike, to be played at the Bell Sauage vpon the Scaffold, where he that went in his fight faſter backe then he ought, of Engliſhman or Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, ſhold be in danger to breake his necke off the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. We cauſed to that effect, fiue or ſixe ſcore Bils of challenge to be printed, and ſet vp from <hi>Southwarke</hi> to the Tower, and from thence through <hi>London</hi> vnto <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:17956:40"/> we were at the place with all theſe weapons at the time apointed, within a bow ſhot of their Fence ſchoole: many gentlemen of good accompt, caried ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the bils of chalenge vnto them, telling them that now the <hi>Siluers</hi> were at the place appointed, with all their weapons, looking for them, and a multitude of people there to behold the fight, ſaying vnto them, now come and go with vs (you ſhall take no wrong) or elſe you are ſhamed for euer. Do the gentlemen what they could, theſe gallants would not come to the place of triall. I verily thinke their cowardly feare to anſwere this chalenge, had vtterly ſhamed them indeed, had not the maiſters of Defence of <hi>London,</hi> within two or three daies after, bene drinking of bottell Ale hard by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centios</hi> ſchoole, in a Hall where the <hi>Italians</hi> muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie paſſe through to go to their ſchoole: and as they were comming by, the maiſters of Defence did pray them to drinke with them, but the <hi>Italians</hi> being verie cowardly, were afraide, and preſently drew their Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers: there was a pretie wench ſtanding by, that loued the <hi>Italians,</hi> ſhe ran with outcrie into the ſtreet, helpe, helpe, the <hi>Italians</hi> are like to be ſlaine: the people with all ſpeede came running into the houſe, and with their Cappes and ſuch things as they could get, parted the fraie, for the Engliſh maiſters of Defence, meant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then to foile their handes vpon theſe two faint-harted fellowes. The next morning after, all the Court was filled, that the <hi>Italian</hi> teachers of Fence had beaten all the maiſters of Defence in <hi>London,</hi> who ſet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them in a houſe together. This wan the <hi>Italian</hi> Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers their credit againe, and thereby got much, ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing their falſe teaching to the end of their liues.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:17956:41"/>
            <p>This <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentio</hi> proued himſelfe a ſtout man not long before he died, that it might be ſeene in his life time he had bene a gallant, and therefore no maruaile he tooke vpon him ſo highly to teach Engliſhmen to fight, and to ſet forth bookes of the feates of Armes. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a time at <hi>Wels</hi> in Somerſetſhire, as he was in great brauerie amongſt manie gentlemen of good accompt, with great boldneſſe he gaue out ſpeeches, that he had bene thus manie yeares in <hi>England,</hi> and ſince the time of his firſt comming, there was not yet one Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that could once touch him at the ſingle Rapier, or Rapier and Dagger. A valiant gentleman being there amongſt the reſt, his Engliſh hart did riſe to heare this proude boaſter, ſecretly ſent a meſſenger to one <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew Bramble</hi> a friend of his, a verie tall man both of his hands and perſon, who kept a ſchoole of Defence in the towne, the meſſenger by the way made the maiſter of Defence acquainted with the mind of the gentleman that ſent for him, and of all what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentio</hi> had ſaid, this maiſter of Defence preſently came, and amongſt all the gentlemen with his cap off, prayed maiſter <hi>Vincentio,</hi> that he would be pleaſed to take a quart of wine of him. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentio</hi> verie ſcornefully looking vpon him, ſaid vnto him. Wherefore ſhould you giue me a quart of wine? Marie Sir, ſaid he, becauſe I heare you are a famous man at your weapon. Then preſently ſaid the gentleman that ſent for the maiſter of Defence: Maiſter <hi>Vincentio,</hi> I pray you bid him welcome, he is a man of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. My profeſſion ſaid <hi>Vincentio?</hi> what is my profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Then ſaid the gentleman, he is a maiſter of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſcience of Defence. Why ſaid maiſter <hi>Vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio,</hi> God make him a good man. But the maiſter of Defence wold
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17956:41"/> not thus leaue him, but pryaed him againe he would be pleaſed to take a quart of wine of him. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid <hi>Vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio,</hi> I haue no need of thy wine. Then ſaid the maiſter of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: Sir I haue a ſchoole of Defence in the towne, will it pleaſe you to go thither. Thy ſchoole, ſaid maiſter <hi>Vincentio?</hi> what ſhall I do at thy ſchoole? play with me (ſaid the maiſter) at the Rapier and Dagger, if it pleaſe you. Play with thee ſaid maiſter <hi>Vincentio?</hi> if I play with thee, I will hit thee 1. 2. 3. 4. thruſtes in the eie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then ſaid the maiſter of Defence, if you can do ſo, it is the better for you, and the worſe for me, but ſurely I can hardly beleeue that you can hit me: but yet once againe I hartily pray you good Sir, that you will go to my ſchoole, and play with me. Play with thee ſaid mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Vincentio</hi> (verie ſcornefully?) by God me ſcorne to play with thee. With that word ſcorne, the maiſter of Defence was verie much moued, and vp with his great Engliſh fiſt, and ſtroke maiſter <hi>Vincentio</hi> ſuch a boxe on the eare that he fell ouer and ouer, his legges iuſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Butterie hatch, whereon ſtood a great blacke Iacke: the maiſter of Defence fearing the worſt, againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentio</hi> his riſing, catcht the blacke Iacke into his hand, being more then halfe full of Beere. <hi>Vincentio</hi> lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily ſtart vp, laying his hand vpon his Dagger, &amp; with the other hand pointed with his finger, ſaying, very well: I will cauſe to lie in the Gaile for this geare, 1. 2. 3 4. yeares. And well ſaid the maiſter of Defence, ſince you will drinke no wine, will you pledge me in Beere? I drinke to all the cowardly knaues in <hi>England,</hi> and I thinke thee to be the verieſt coward of them all: with that he caſt all the Beere vpon him: notwithſtanding <hi>Vincentio</hi> hauing nothing but his guilt Rapier, and
<pb n="07" facs="tcp:17956:42"/> Dagger about him, and the other for his defence the blacke Iacke, would not at that time fight it out: but the next day met with the maiſter of Defence in the ſtreete, and ſaid vnto him, you remember how miſuſed a me yeſterday, you were to blame, me be an excellent man, me teach you how to thruſt two foote further then anie Engliſhman, but firſt come you with me: then he brought him to a Mercers ſhop, and ſaid to the Mercer, let me ſee of your beſt ſilken Pointes, the Mercer did preſently ſhew him ſome of ſeauen groates a dozen, then he payeth fourteene groates for two dozen, and ſaid to the maiſter of Defence, there is one dozen for you, and here is another for me. This was one of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianteſt Fencers that came from beyond the ſeas, to teach Engliſhmen to fight, and this was one of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt frayes, that I haue hard of, that euer he made in <hi>England,</hi> wherin he ſhewed himſelfe a farre better man in his life, then in his profeſſion he was, for he profeſſed armes, but in his life a better Chriſtian. He ſet forth in print a booke for the vſe of the Rapier and Dagger, the which he called his practiſe, I haue read it ouer, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I finde therein neither true rule for the perfect teaching of true fight, nor true ground of true fight, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſence or reaſon for due proofe thereof. I haue thought it friuolous to recite any part therin contained: yet that the truth hereof may appeare, let two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being wel experienced in the Rapier and Dagger fight, chooſe any of the beſt branches in the ſame booke, &amp; make trial with force and agility, without the which the truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the true &amp; falſe fight cannot be knowne, &amp; they ſhall find great imperfections therein. And againe, for proofe that there is no truth, neither in his rules, grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17956:42"/> or Rapier-fight, let triall be made in this maner:<note place="margin">Proofes againſt the Rapier fight.</note> Set two vnskilfull men together at the Rapier and Dagger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing valiant, and you ſhall ſee, that once in two boutes there ſhall either one or both of them be hurt. Then ſet two skilfull men together, being valiant at the Rapier and Dagger, and they ſhall do the like. Then ſet a skilful Rapier and Dagger-man the beſt that can be had, and a valiant man hauing no skill together at Rapier &amp; Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and once in two bouts vpon my credit in all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I haue in fight, the vnskilful man, do the other what he can for his life to the contrarie, ſhall hurt him, and moſt commonly if it were in continuance of fight, you ſhall ſee the vnskilfull man to haue the aduantage. And if I ſhould chuſe a valiant man for ſeruice of the Prince, or to take part with me or anie friend of mine in a good quarrell, I would chuſe the vnskilfull man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnencombred with falſe fights, becauſe ſuch a man ſtandeth free in his valour with ſtrength and agilitie of bodie, freely taketh the benefit of nature, fighteth moſt braue, by looſing no oportunitie, either ſoundly to hurt his enemie, or defend himſelfe, but the other ſtanding for his Defence, vpon his cunning Italian wardes, <hi>Poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta reuerſa,</hi> the <hi>Imbrocata, Stocata,</hi> and being faſt tyed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe falſe fightes, ſtandeth troubled in his wits, and nature therby racked through the largeneſſe or falſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or Spaces, whereby he is in his fight as a man halfe maimed, looſing the oportunity of times &amp; benefit of nature, &amp; whereas before being ignorant of theſe falſe Rapier fightes, ſtanding in the free libertie of nature giuen him by god, he was able in the field with his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to anſwere the valianteſt man in the world, but now being tied vnto that falſe fickle vncertaine fight, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17956:43"/> hath loſt in nature his freedome, is now become ſcarce halfe a man, and euerie boye in that fight is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as good a man as himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieronimo</hi> this gallant was valiant, and would fight indeed, and did, as you ſhall heare. He being in a Coch with a wench that he loued well, there was one <hi>Cheeſe,</hi> a verie tall man, in his fight naturall Engliſh, for he fought with his Sword and Dagger, and in Rapier-fight had no skill at all. This <hi>Cheeſe</hi> hauing a quarrell to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronimo,</hi> ouertooke him vpon the way, himſelfe being on horſebacke, did call to <hi>Ieronimo,</hi> and bad him come forth of the Coch or he would fetch him, for he was come to fight with him. <hi>Ieronimo</hi> preſently went forth of the Coch and drew his Rapier and dagger, put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into his beſt ward or <hi>Stocata,</hi> which ward was taught by himſelfe and <hi>Vincentio,</hi> and by them beſt allowed of, to be the beſt ward to ſtand vpon in fight for life, either to aſſault the enemie, or ſtand and watch his comming, which ward it ſhould ſeeme he ventured his life vpon, but howſoeuer with all the fine Italienated skill <hi>Ieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> had, <hi>Cheeſe</hi> with his Sword within two thruſtes ran him into the bodie and ſlue him. Yet the Italian tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers will ſay, that an Engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cannot thruſt ſtraight with a Sword, becauſe the hilt will not ſuffer him to put the forefinger ouer the Croſſe, nor to put the thumbe vpon the blade, nor to hold the pummell in the hand, whereby we are of neceſſitie to hold faſt the handle in the hand: by reaſon whereof we are driuen to thruſt both compaſſe and ſhort, whereas with the Rapier they can thruſt both ſtraight and much further then we can with the Sword, becauſe of the hilt: and theſe be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they make againſt the Sword.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17956:43"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
